He will be saying prayers in the garden.
甘地将于花园中祷告
Just follow the others.
请随着众人走
Brother, Bapu is already late for prayers.
弟兄，巴布祷告已经迟了
Oh, God!
上帝…
The object of this massive tribute...
这个盛大葬礼的死者
...died as he had always lived:
死时与他活着的时候一样
A private man...
一个平民
...without wealth...
没有任何的财富
...without property...
没有任何的财产
...without official title or office.
也没任何的官衔
Mahatma Gandhi...
圣雄甘地
...was not the commander of armies...
既不是军事将领
...nor a ruler of vast lands.
也不是地方首长
He could not boast any scientific achievement...
也没任何科学成就可以夸耀
...or artistic gift.
也不是一个名艺术家
Yet men...
然而世界各地人士
...governments, dignitaries from all over the world...
包括各政府代表及高官贵人
...have joined hands today to pay homage...
在此齐聚一堂
...to this little brown man in the loincloth...
向这位绑着缠腰布的棕肤色小个子
...who led his country to freedom.
致最后的敬意 他领导印度走向自由
In the words of General George C. Marshall...
诚如美国国务卿
...the American Secretary of State:
马歇尔所说
"Mahatma Gandhi has become the spokesman...
圣雄甘地是人类良心的
...for the conscience of all mankind.
代言者
He was a man...
他就是
...who made humility...
使得谦虚
...and simple truth...
及真理的力量
...more powerful than Empires."
能够战胜帝国
And Albert Einstein added:
爱因斯坦则说
"Generations to come will scarce believe that such a one as this...
后代子孙将无法相信
...ever in flesh and blood...
世上曾经活生生的
...walked upon this earth."
出现过这号人物
Tell me...
告诉我
...do you think about hell?
你曾经有想过地狱这回事吗
Neither do I.
我也没想过
But this man here...
可是这位仁兄
...is a Christian, and he's written that in order to believe...
是基督徒，写说为了相信…
Excuse me, sir.
对不起，先生
How long have you been in South Africa?
请问您来南非多久了
A week.
一个星期
I don't know how you got a ticket.
我不知道你是怎么买到票的
Just what are you doing in this car, coolie?
你在这个车厢里干嘛 印度阿三
Why, I have a ticket.
怎样，我有车票
A first-class ticket.
头等舱的票
- How did you get it? - I sent for it in the post.
-你是怎么买到票的 -用邮购的方式
I'm an attorney. I didn't...
我是律师，没有时间…
There are no colored attorneys in South Africa.
南非没有有色人种的律师
Sit where you belong!
去坐你该坐的地方
I'll take your luggage back, sir.
我帮你把行李拿过去
Just a moment, please.
等一下
You see...
你看
...Mohandas K. Gandhi...
莫罕德甘地
...Attorney at Law.
律师
I'm on my way to Pretoria to conduct a case for an Indian trading firm.
我正要去普利托里亚 为一个印度公司辩护
Didn't you hear me?
你没听到吗
There are no colored attorneys in South Africa.
南非没有有色人种的律师
I was called to the Bar in London...
我在伦敦考取律师资格
...and enrolled at the High Court of Chancery.
是正式登记 在大法官法庭的一员
I am, therefore, an attorney.
所以我是律师
And since I am, in your eyes, colored...
既然我在你眼里是有色人种
...I think we can deduce that there is at least...
我想我们可以推论在南非
...one colored attorney in South Africa.
至少有一个有色人种律师
Smart, bloody Kaffir!
聪明的混蛋土人
Throw him out.
把他扔出去
Just move your black ass back to third class.
滚到三等舱去
Or I'll have you thrown off at the next station.
不然一靠站就把你扔出去
But I always go first class!
但是我一向都坐头等舱…
But you're a rich man. Why put up with it?
可是你是有钱人 为什么要忍受这种事
Yes, I am rich.
我是有钱
But I am Indian.
不过却是印度人
I do not expect to travel first class.
所以不敢奢望能坐头等舱
- In England, I was a poor student. - That was England.
-在英国我只是个穷学生 -那是英国
This is part of England's Empire.
这里也是大英帝国的一部份
Mr. Gandhi, you look at Mr. Khan and you see a successful Muslim trader.
甘地先生，在你眼里 康先生是个成功的回教徒商人
Most South Africans see him simply as an Indian.
在大多数的南非人眼里 他只是个印度人
And the vast majority of Indians, mostly Hindus, like yourself...
而在这里大多的印度人 大半是像你是印度教的
...were brought here to work mines and harvest crops.
都是矿工或者是农场帮手
Most Europeans don't want them doing anything else.
大多的欧洲人 不愿意他们做其他别的工作
But that is very unchristian...
可是这样违背基督教的精神…
Mr. Gandhi, in this country...
甘地先生，在南非
...lndians are not allowed to walk along the pavement with a Christian.
印度人不允许 和基督徒一起走在人行道上
You mean, you employ Mr. Baker as your attorney...
你聘请贝克先生做你的律师
...but you can't walk down the street with him?
却不能跟他一起上街
Well, I can.
我可以
But I risk being kicked into the gutter by someone...
不过要冒会被一个三流人物
...less holy than Mr. Baker.
踢下水沟的危险
Well, then it must be fought.
一定要反抗
We are children of God like everyone else.
我们都是上帝的子民
Allah be praised!
赞美阿拉
And what battalions will you call upon?
你打算如何召集人马来对抗
I will write to the press...
我要写信给南非的报社
...here and in England.
还有英国的
I will use the courts.
我还要告到法院去…
You'll cause a lot of trouble. Our position is...
你会引起大骚动，反对是…
We are members of the Empire.
印度也是大英帝国的一份子
And we come from an ancient civilization.
是个文明古国
Why should we not walk on the pavements like other men?
为什么我们不能跟别人一样 一起走在人行道上
I rather like the idea of an Indian barrister in South Africa.
印度大律师在南非 我喜欢这个主意
I'm sure our community could keep you in work for some time...
我相信印度人 会让你生意不断，忙一阵子
...even if you caused a good deal of trouble.
即使你会惹上大麻烦
Especially if you caused
尤其是在你惹上大麻烦的时候
There's the English reporter. I told you he'd come.
那个英国记者在那里 我说过他会来的
You also said your article would draw a thousand people.
你也说了 你的文章会引来一千个人
At least some of the Hindus...
至少有些印度教徒
...brought their wives.
带太太来了
No, I asked my wife to organize that.
不，是我要求我太太 召集她们来的
Some of them are leaving.
有些人要走了
Ladies and gentlemen...
各位先生女士
...we have asked you to gather here to help us proclaim our right...
我之所以要求你们来此 是为了要帮助印度人争取
...to be treated as equal citizens of the Empire.
大英帝国子民的平等权利
We do not seek conflict.
我们不想引发冲突
We know the strength of the forces arrayed against us...
也了解对手力量庞大
...know that because of them, we can only use peaceful means.
也了解正因如此 我们只能用和平的方法
But we are determined that justice will be done.
可是我们意志坚决 正义一定得以伸张
The symbol of our status is embodied in this pass...
我们地位的象征 竟然在这张通行证上
...which we must carry at all times...
我们必须随时带在身上
...but which no European even has to have.
而欧洲人却根本不需要有
The first step towards changing our status...
改变我们地位的第一步
...is to eliminate this difference between us.
就是消除这点差别待遇
Now?
那么…
You write brilliantly, but you have much to learn about handling men.
你的文笔很不错 不过还得学习掌握群众的窍门
We do not want to ignite...
我们不想引发
...the fear or hatred of anyone.
任何的恐惧或怨恨的情绪
But we ask you...
但是我们要求你们
...Hindu, Muslim and Sikh...
印度教徒，回教徒和锡克教徒
...to help us light up the sky...
以反抗此不公平制度之行动
...and the minds of the British authorities...
帮助我们照亮天空
...with our defiance of this injustice.
也照亮英国当局的心灵
We will now burn the passes of our committee and its supporters.
现在我们就把 我们支持者的通行证烧毁
We ask you to put your passes on the fire...
我们要求你们 把通行证丢进火里
You bloody dog!
这群浑蛋
Those passes...
这些通行证
...are government property!
是政府的财产
And I will arrest the first man who tries to burn one!
谁要烧毁我就逮捕谁
Take him away.
把他带走
You little...
你这个
...Sammy...
印度
...bastard!
浑帐
Now...
现在
...are there anymore?
还有吗
If you want this kind of trouble, you can have it.
如果要惹麻烦的尽管上来
Let me go!
让我过去
Stop.
停止
The London papers have arrived from the Cape.
伦敦的报纸都到了
The worst was the Daily Mail.
最糟的是每日邮报报导
They said the burning of passes...
甘地烧毁通行证的行为
- Ask Mr. Herzog to see me. - It was the most significant act...
-叫赫先生来见我 -甘地烧毁通行证的行为
...in colonial affairs since the Declaration of Independence.
是英国殖民地自美国独立以来 最具意义的行动
They'll find we're better prepared this time.
这次我们已经有万全的准备
Mr. Gandhi will find he's on a long hiding to nothing.
甘地先生将会毫无所获，平白受苦
"A High Court judge has confirmed that Mr. Gandhi...
一名高等法官证实
...would've been within his rights to prosecute for assault...
甘地先生有权控告政府伤害罪
...since neither he nor Mr. Khan resisted arrest."
因为他和康先生 都并未反抗警方的逮捕行为
I told you about English law.
我跟你说过英国法律是这样的
As I told you about English policemen.
我也跟你说过英国警察是这样的
We're very pleased to have you back, Papa.
爸爸，很高兴你回来了
And I am glad to be back.
我也很高兴能回来
Mind your face.
小心脸
Tomorrow I'll tell you about my days in a police hospital.
明天我把在警方医院里的事 讲给你们听
Come, come.
来
Just like proper English gentlemen. I'm proud of them.
他们就像英国绅士一样 我真以他们为荣
They're boys.
他们还是孩子
And they're Indian.
并且他们是印度人
Will you take this off? It pinches every time I speak.
把绷带拿下来好不好 我一说话就会痛
I've got it.
好
You'd be Gandhi.
你一定是甘地吧
I thought you'd be bigger.
我以为你会壮一点
I'm sorry.
对不起
No, that's all right.
没关系
My name is Charlie Andrews, sir.
我叫查理安德鲁
I've come from India.
我从印度来的
I've read a great deal about you.
我读了很多有关你的报导
Some of it good, I hope.
希望其中有好的方面
Would you care to walk?
想不想走一走
You're a clergyman?
你是神职人员
I met some remarkable people in India.
我在印度 遇到一些很了不起的人
And when I read what you were doing, I wanted to help.
当我知道你在这里的所做所为 我很想助你一臂之力
- Does that surprise you? - Not anymore.
-你觉得意外吗 -不再会了
At first, I was amazed...
开始时我很惊
...but when you're fighting in a just cause...
可是当你在为正义而战时
...people seem to pop up, like you, right out of the pavement.
突然间，就会有很多人 一个个的冒出来，像你一样
Even when it's dangerous or...
即使会有危险…
Hey, look what's coming!
看看什么来了
A white shepherd leading a brown Sammy!
一个白牧羊人带着棕色阿三
Perhaps we should...
或许我们应该…
Doesn't the New Testament say:
新约上不是说
"If your enemy strikes you on the right cheek, offer him the left"?
“敌人打你的右脸颊，左脸也让他打”
The phrase was used metaphorically. I don't think our Lord...
这个说法只是种比喻 我想上帝…
I'm not so sure.
我不那么认为
I have thought about it a great deal.
我常想到这句话
I suspect He meant you must show courage...
我想这可能是指 人必须有勇气
...be willing to take a blow, several blows, to show...
愿意接受打击，多次的打击
...you won't strike back, nor will you be turned aside.
以证明自己不还手但也不退让
And when you do that, it calls on something in human nature...
这样做就能唤起人类的本性
...that makes his hatred for you decrease and his respect increase.
减少对方的恨意 使对方能有尊敬之心
I think Christ grasped that, and I have seen it work.
我想耶稣领悟到个中奥妙 而我也曾亲身体验
Good morning.
早安
Get off the pavement, you bloody coon.
离开人行道，你这个混蛋老黑
- Yeah, get off. - Kaffir!
-滚开 -土人
Colin, what are you doing?
柯林，你在干什么
Nothing.
没有
Come out where I can see you!
走出来，让我看得到你
I said, what are you doing?
你在做什么
We were just trying to clean up the neighborhood.
我们只是想让本区干净点
You're late for work. I thought you'd gone ten minutes ago.
你上班迟到了 我以为你十分钟前就走了
Get on!
快去
You'll find there's room for us all.
你会发现人人都有立足之地
- That was lucky. - I thought you were a man of God.
-运气真好 -我以为你是信奉上帝的
I am, but I'm not so egotistical as to think...
我是，不过可没自大到
...He plans His day around my dilemmas.
以为神会永远帮我解困
You could call it a communal farm, I suppose.
我想你可以称它为自治农场
But you've all come to the same conclusions.
不过你们都有相同的结论
Our Gita, the Muslim's Koran, your Bible.
我们的经文 回教的可兰经，你们的圣经
It's always the simple things that catch your breath.
让人顿悟的 都是一些简单的东西
"Love thy neighbor as thyself."
爱怜人就如爱自己
Not always practiced...
不是人人做得到的
...but it's something we Hindus could learn a lot from.
不过这点是我们 印度教人应该多学习的
That's the kind of thing you'll be seeking on this farm?
这也是你在这个农场 想找到的东西
Well, we shall try.
我们会努力的
Bad news, I'm afraid.
恐怕是坏消息
They're going to change the pass laws.
他们要修改通行证的法律
It's taken time...
需要时间
...but it needed to be done fairly.
不过必须要公平
We didn't want to create an injustice simply because Mr. Gandhi...
我们不愿意因为甘地先生 污蔑我们现有的法律
...was abusing our existing legislation.
就制定不公正的制度
Just one moment, sir, please.
一下就好，大人
I beg your pardon.
对不起
But on a short trip...
你停留的时间那么短
...I wouldn't spend too much time on the Indian question, Mr. Walker.
不必浪费太多的时间 在印度的问题上
It's a tiny factor in South African life.
这只是南非生活的小小涟漪
Well, it is news at the moment.
目前是新闻
I plan to report on the condition of the mines here...
当然除了经济方面
...as well as the economy.
我也计划报导矿场方面的事
But I would like to meet this Mr. Gand-eye.
不过我想见见这个甘德斯
Gandhi.
甘地…
Of course. We Westerners have a weakness...
当然，西方人都会喜欢这类
...for these spiritually inclined men of India.
谈经论神的印度人
But as an old lawyer, let me warn you.
不过我以老律师的资格警告你
Mr. Gandhi is as shrewd a man as you will ever meet...
不论看起来多超世脱俗
...however otherworldly he may seem.
甘地先生是极精明的人
But I'm sure you're enough of a reporter to see that.
不过我相信像你这么好的记者 一定看得出来
I hope so. Thank you for your time, sir.
希望如此，多谢您接受访问
So it's not spiritualism or nationalism.
既非违心论，也非民族主义
We're not resisting anything...
我们只是反对
...but the idea that people can't live together.
种族信仰隔离的这种思想
You see?
看见吗？
Hindus, Muslims...
印度教徒，回教徒
...Sikhs, Jews...
锡克教，犹太教
...even Christians.
甚至基督徒
Mr. Walker of the New York Times.
纽约时报的华克先生
How you doing?
你好
Without a paper, a journal of some kind...
一个群体需要报纸或是
...you cannot unite a community.
某种新闻媒体才能团结起来
You belong to a very important profession.
你这行是很重要的行业
And what do you think an important professional should write...
你觉得这个重要的行业 该怎么报导
...about your response to General Smuts' newest legislation?
你对史莫兹将军新立法的反应
I don't know.
我不知道
I'm still searching for a response.
我还在想该如何反应
You will respect the law?
你会尊重法律
There are unjust laws as there are unjust men.
有不公正的法律 正如有不公正的人
You're a small minority to take on the South African government...
对抗南非政府 以你们的人数是微乎其微
...not to mention the British Empire.
更别提对抗大英帝国了
If you are a minority of one...
就算你是唯一反抗的人
...the truth is the truth.
真理却永远是真理
Herman Kallenbach...
贺曼可朗北
...our chief carpenter, also our chief benefactor.
木匠工头，也是我们主要的赞功人
Vince Walker, New York Times.
文思华克，纽约时报的人
This is quite a place you've got here.
你们这个地方真不错
And you call it an ashram?
-你称它为“阿思朗” -是的
That's right. The word only means "community."
意思是社区
But it could stand for "village" or "the world."
不过也能代表村庄或世界
You're an ambitious man, Mr. Gandhi.
你的野心很大，甘地先生
I hope not.
我希望不会
I hear that you also prepare the meals and clean the toilets.
听说你本人也亲自煮饭 还有清洗厕所
- Is that part of the experiment? - Ba!
-这是实验的一部份吗 -芭
We will need another place set for Mr. Walker's driver.
给华克先生的司机 准备一个座位
I will tell Tara.
我会告诉泰拉
Yes, it's one way to learn that each man's labor...
这样可以让人了解
...is as important as another's.
劳力无贫富之分
While you're doing it, cleaning the toilet...
事实上，当在洗厕所时
...seems far more important than the law.
你会觉得洗厕所比法律重要
Please, come and join us.
请和我们一起用餐
You'll need something before your journey back.
回去前得先吃点东西
- Would you excuse me, please? - Yeah, sure.
-能不能失陪一下 -当然
What is it?
什么事
Sora was sent to tell me I must...
苏拉来告诉我
...rake and cover the latrine.
我必须扫粪除屎
That's right.
对
Everyone takes their turn.
大家轮流的
It is the work of untouchables!
这是下级贱民做的
In this place, there are no untouchables.
这里没有所谓的下级贱民
And no work is beneath any of us.
也没有分那些是低贱的工作
I'm your wife!
我是你妻子
All the more reason.
那更应该要做
As you command.
遵命
The others may follow you, but you forget...
其他人是你的信徒 可是你忘了
...I knew you when you were a boy.
我们从小就认识的
It's not me.
不是我要你做
It's the principle.
这是原则问题
And you will do it with joy or not do it at all.
你如果不能心甘情愿的做 就根本别做
Not at all then.
那我不做
All right then, go. You don't belong here!
好，那你走，你不属于这里
Leave the ashram altogether. We don't want you!
离开这里，走，我们不要你
Have you no shame?
你没羞耻心吗？
I'm your wife!
我是你的妻子
Where do you expect me to go?
你要我去哪里
What's the matter with me?
我是怎么了
You're human.
你只是个人
Only human.
只是个人
And it's even harder for those of us...
对根本不想做的跟你
...who do not even want to be as good as you do.
一样好的人而言会更加困难
I apologize.
我道歉
I must get back to that reporter.
我得回去跟那个记者谈谈
And I must...
我必须去
...rake and cover the latrine.
扫粪除屎
I want to welcome you all.
我欢迎所有的人
Every one of you.
你们所有的人
We have no secrets.
我们没有秘密
Let us begin by being clear...
我们先来澄清
...about General Smuts' new law.
史莫兹将军的新法律
All Indians must now be fingerprinted...
所有的印度人都必须留下指纹
...like criminals.
就像犯罪
Men and women.
不论男女
No marriage other than a Christian marriage is considered valid.
婚姻如果没举行基督教仪式 就视为无效
Under this act...
在这个法律之下
...our wives and mothers are whores.
我们的太太和母亲全是妓女
And every man here is a bastard.
所有的男人都是杂种
He has become quite good at this.
他变的相当在行了
And a policeman...
当警察
...passing an Indian dwelling...
经过印度人的住处
...I will not call them homes...
那可算不上是个家
...may enter and demand the card of any Indian woman whose dwelling it is.
可以任意进入要求查看 住在里面的任何男女之证件
Goddamn them!
去他们的
Understand...
明白吗
...he does not have to stand at the door.
他不需要站在门口
He may enter.
他就可以直接进去
I will not allow it!
我绝对不让他进我家
I swear to Allah.
我对阿拉发誓
I'll kill the man who offers that insult to my home and my wife...
谁敢如此污辱我家 和我太太的话，我一定宰了他
...and let them hang me!
让他们吊死我好了
I say: Talk means nothing!
我认为空谈无义
Kill a few officials before they disgrace one Indian woman.
先杀他几个警察 免得他们玷污印度女性
Then they might think twice about such laws.
这样就会对法律加以三思
In that cause, I would be willing to die!
为此我愿意牺牲
I praise such courage.
我很钦佩你的勇气
I need such courage...
我也需要这种勇气
...because, in this cause, I too am prepared to die.
因为我也愿意为此主义而牺牲
But, my friend...
但是，我的朋友
...there is no cause for which I am prepared to kill.
我不会为任何主义而杀人
Whatever they do to us...
不论他们怎么对待我们
...we will attack no one...
我们绝不还击
...kill no one.
绝不杀人
But we will not give our fingerprints, not one of us.
但是我们也绝不印指纹 谁也不印
They will imprison us. They will fine us.
他们将会把我们关起来 罚我们钱
They will seize our possessions.
没收我们的财产
But they cannot take away our self-respect...
可是只要我们坚持
...if we do not give it to them.
绝不能抢走我们的自尊
Have you been to prison?
你坐过牢吗
They beat us and torture us. I say...
他们会拷打我们，折磨我们 我说我们应该…
I am asking you to fight.
我要求你与其对抗
To fight against their anger, not to provoke it.
就对抗他们的愤怒 而不是挑起他们的愤怒
We will not strike a blow.
我们绝不攻击他们
But we will receive them.
可是我们将承受攻击
And through our pain...
经由我们承受的痛苦
...we will make them see their injustice.
他们会看清自己的不公正
And it will hurt...
这和攻击他们
...as all fighting hurts.
一样的具有杀伤力
But we cannot lose.
但是我们不能输
We cannot.
绝对不能
They may torture my body...
他们可以折磨我
...break my bones...
打断我的骨头
...even kill me.
甚至杀了我
Then...
而他们所得
...they will have my dead body...
只是一具尸体
...not my obedience.
而不是我的屈服
We are Hindu and Muslim...
我们是印度教徒和回教徒
...children of God, each one of us.
都是神的子民，每个都是
Let us take a solemn oath in His name...
让我们以神的名义来发誓
...that, come what may...
不论如何
...we will not submit to this law.
绝不向此法律低头
God save our gracious King
上帝保佑英王陛下
God save our noble King
上帝保佑高贵的英王
God save our King
上帝保佑英王
These men are contracted laborers.
这些人是签了约的劳工
They belong in the mines.
他们属于矿场所有
You put their comrades in jail.
他们的同志被关起来了
When you free them...
只要放了他们
...they will go back to work.
这些人马上工作
I've warned you.
我警告过你了
We've warned each other.
我们彼此警告过了
I don't think that's very good.
我想情况不太妙
Steady, steady.
稳住
Stop!
停！
At the canter, charge!
攻击正中间
We should lie down.
我们应该躺下来
Down!
躺下…
The horses won't trample on us. Lie down!
那些马不会踏我们的
Follow me!
好吧，算了，跟我来…
Now what the hell do we do?
现在我们要怎么办
Let them march.
让他们游行
In our own sweet time, in our own sweet way...
在时机对的时候 自然会有好办法
...we'll get them.
来对付他们
One law!
同样的法律
One king!
同样的国王
Some of you may be rejoicing that Mr. Gandhi...
或许有些人正庆幸 甘地先生
...has at last been put into prison.
总算被关起来了
But I would ask you, assembled here in this house of God...
但是我要求各位 聚集在这神的殿堂中
...to recognize that we are witnessing something new...
认清我们亲眼目睹新的事物
...something so unexpected, so unusual...
如此出人意料 如此不寻常
...that it is not surprising the government is at a loss.
难怪会让政府不知所措
What Mr. Gandhi has forced us to do...
甘地先生迫使我们做的
...is ask questions about ourselves.
是要我们扪心自问
As Christians, those are difficult questions to answer.
身为基督徒 这种问题很难回答
How do we treat men who defy an unjust law...
我们该如何对待
...who will not fight...
一个抗拒不公平的法律
...but will not comply?
但是既不攻击政府也不屈服的人
As Christians or as people who have not heard the word of...
不论是身为基督徒 或身为一个没有宗教
They're sparing no one, I see.
我看他们一个也没放过
No, you were the surprise.
不放过你才令人惊
It has been all over the prison.
全监狱都知道了
We thought they'd be too afraid of the English press.
我还以为他们会太害怕英国新闻界
So did I.
我也是
I don't know who they've left out there to do the work.
外面还有人在挖矿吗
Have they touched the women?
他们也逮捕女人吗
My wife publicly defied the law. They've arrested her and four others.
我妻子公开反对这种法律 他们逮捕了她和另外四个
It split the government.
政府因此产生歧见
Well, that's one victory.
这是一个胜利
If we hold firm, it won't be the last.
只要我们坚定不屈 就能继续赢下去
Don't worry.
放心
I've never seen men so determined.
我从没见过 这么坚定的群众
You have given them a way to fight.
你指引他们一个对抗的途径
Gandhi!
甘地
I want Gandhi!
我要找甘地
Which Sammy is it?
是哪一个印度阿三
Mr. Gandhi.
甘地先生
I thought we might have a little talk.
我想我们可以商量一下
Thank you, Daniels.
谢谢你，丹尼尔
Will you have a glass of sherry?
要不要喝点酒
Thank you, no.
谢谢，不用了
Perhaps some tea?
喝茶吗
I dined at the prison.
我在牢里吃过了
Please.
请
Do come and sit down.
过来坐下
I've more or less decided to ask the House to repeal the act...
我多少决定了要请求议会
...that you have taken such exception to.
重审你特别关切的那个法案
Well, if you asked, General Smuts, I'm sure it will be done.
如果你提出请求 我相信他们一定会重审
It's not quite that simple.
没那么简单
Somehow, I expected not.
我早只如此
I thought of calling for a royal commission...
我想要召集皇家委员会
...to investigate the new legislation.
来调查这个新立法
I think I could guarantee they would recommend the act be repealed.
我想我可以保证 他们会建议重审这个法案
I congratulate them.
我恭喜他们
But they might also recommend...
但是他们也可能建议要
...that all future Indian immigration be severely restricted...
严格限制之后的印度移民来此
...even stopped.
甚至予以终止
Immigration was not an issue on which we fought.
我们这次并不想争取移民
It would be wrong of us to make it one now that we...
现在起而争取是不对的
We are in a position of advantage.
这样是在利用有利的情势
I'm ordering the release of all prisoners within the next 24 hours.
我已经下令在24小时之内 释放所有的犯人
You yourself are free as from this moment.
而你此刻就自由了
Assuming we are in agreement.
只要你也同意的话
It's just that in these clothes, I would prefer...
只是穿这身衣服我希望能…
...to go by taxi.
坐计程车
All right. Fine.
好
I'm afraid I have no money.
可是我身上没钱
Neither have I.
我也没有
I'm awfully sorry.
很抱歉
Daniels...
丹尼尔
...will you lend Mr. Gandhi a shilling for a taxi?
能不能借一先令 给甘地先生坐计程车
I beg your pardon, sir?
您说什么，先生
How far will you be going, Gandhi?
你要去哪里
Now that this is settled, I'd thought seriously of going back to India.
事情既然已经决定 我很想要回印度去
But a shilling will do splendidly for the moment.
不过目前一先令就够了
Thank you.
谢谢你
I'm obliged, Mr. Daniels...
我心领了
...but I can find my own way out.
不过我想我自己能找到路出去
Guard of honor!
仪队注意！
Attention!
立正
Present arms!
仪队举枪
- My God, he loves it! - I'm sure he hates it.
-天啊，他爱死这样了 -不，他讨厌这样
Generals' reputations are being made in France today...
今天在法国西方前线作战
...fighting on the Western front.
的将军大出风头
Not as military governors in India.
他们绝不会当印度的军事总督
What the devil's going on back there?
那边是怎么回事
Must be that Indian who made all that fuss in Africa.
一定是在非洲没事找事 小题大作的那个印度人
My cabin boy told me he was on board.
我的小厮告诉我他也在船上
There he is.
就是他
God, he's dressed like a coolie!
天啊，他穿的像个苦力
I thought he was a lawyer.
我以为他是律师
Mr. Gandhi, have you refused to wear European clothes?
甘地先生，你拒绝穿西服吗
No, I haven't refused.
不，我并没有拒绝穿
I simply wanted to dress the way my comrades in prison dress.
我只是要穿的 和我牢中的朋友一样罢了
Will you support the war effort?
你会帮助英军吗
If I wish to enjoy the benefits and protection of the British Empire...
身为大英帝国公民 希望能分享其利益，受其保护
...it would be wrong of me not to help in its defense.
如果不帮助对抗敌军是错误的
Now that you're back in India what are you going to do?
现在你回到印度了 你有任何打算
I don't know.
我不知道
- I don't know. - One more question.
-我不知道 -甘地先生，最后一个问题…
As an Indian woman, how could you accept the indignity of prison?
身为印度女性 你如何面对坐牢这种屈辱
My dignity comes from following my husband.
只要能追随我丈夫 我就不觉得受屈辱
Thank you very much.
非常谢谢你
Just a few words, then we'll get you to civilization.
只要说几句话 我们就送你重返文明社会中
May I?
可以吗？
I'm glad to be home...
我很高兴能回到祖国
...and I thank you for your greeting.
谢谢你们如此的欢迎我
I'll follow with your wife.
我跟你太太一车
Don't worry. Everything's arranged.
放心，一切都安排妥当了
Who's that young man?
那个年轻人是谁
That's young Nehru.
那是小尼鲁
He's got his father's intellect, his mother's good looks...
他兼具了父亲的智慧 和母亲的美貌
...and the devil's own charm.
加上魔鬼的魅力
If they don't ruin him at Cambridge. Wave, wave!
如果剑桥不把他毁了… 挥手…
He might amount to something.
他可能会有所成就
I must say, when I first saw you...
我承认，我刚认识你时
...as a bumbling lawyer here in Bombay...
你是一个在孟买的新进律师
...I never thought I'd greet you as a national hero.
没想到有朝一日 会来欢迎你这个国家英雄
I'm hardly that, Mr. Patel.
我算不上是国家英雄
Yes, you are!
你是的
It's been two hundred years since an Indian cocked a snook...
两百年来能如此藐视大英帝国
...at the British Empire and got away with it.
而且平安无事的印度人 就只有你而已
And stop calling me Mr. Patel. You're not a junior clerk anymore.
别叫我彼帖先生 你不是新进职员了
The new military governor of the Northwest Province was on that ship.
西北省的军事总督 也搭乘这班船
Too bad you came back third class.
可惜你是坐三等舱
He might have been impressed...
不然他一定会对你一个在策略上
...by a successful barrister who'd outmaneuvered General Smuts.
战胜了史莫兹将军的律师 印象深刻
Yes, I'm sure.
我想是会的
Are you involved too, Mrs. Nehru?
尼鲁夫人，你也参加吗
No. I leave practical matters to my husband...
不…实际的事都交给我丈夫
...and revolution to my son.
革命的事就交给我儿子
Mr. Gandhi, I'd like you to meet Mr. Jinnah, our joint host...
甘地先生 这位是吉纳先生，宴会的主人
...member of Congress and leader of the Muslim League...
他是国会议员，回教领袖
How do you do?
你好
...and Mr. Prakash, who, I fear...
这位是派卡区先生
...is awaiting trial for sedition and inducement to murder.
他正要为妨害治安 和意图谋杀之罪而接受审判
I have not actually pulled the trigger, Mr. Gandhi.
我并没有真的扣扳机杀人
I have simply written...
我只是写了文章说
...if an Englishman kills an Indian for disobeying his law...
如果英国人杀了违反英法的印度人
...it is an Indian's duty to kill an Englishman...
印度人因为英国人在
...for enforcing his law in a land that is not his.
不属于他们的土地上实行英法 就应该杀英国人
It's a clever argument. I'm not sure it'll produce the end you desire.
很聪明的辩论，不过我没把握 这就能获得你要的结果
We hope you'll join us in our struggle for home rule, Mr. Gandhi.
希望你能加入我们 争取制定自治法律的奋斗
Excuse me. May I, Mohan? There's someone I'd like him to meet.
对不起，甘地 我要你来见一个人
Excuse me.
失陪了
Sorry to rush you.
抱歉这样催你
He told the press he'd support the British in the war.
他对新闻界说 他将支持英国对抗敌军
That's nonviolence for you.
那才不是非暴力
You know, Mohan...
甘地，请你谅解
...now I have a confession to make.
有件事我要忏悔
I didn't decide to come to South Africa.
我并不是自愿去南非的
Professor Gokhale sent me.
是哥汉教授派我去的
We are trying to make a nation, Gandhi.
我们想建立一个国家
But the British keep trying to break us up...
可是英国却利用
...into religions, principalities, provinces.
宗教，阶级，省份来分化印度
What you were writing in South Africa...
你在南非所写的
...that's what we need here.
正是这里所需要的
I have so much to learn about India.
我对印度的了解还不够
And I have to begin my practice again.
而且我必须再度执业了
One needs money to run a journal.
我需要钱办杂志
Nonsense. Go on, Charlie, This is Indian talk.
胡说，查理，你先离开 这是印度人的谈话
We want none of you imperialists here.
不要你这个帝国人士夹在中间
All right, I'll go and write my report to the Viceroy.
好，那我去写报告给总督
You go and find a pretty Hindu woman...
去找个信印度教的漂亮小姐
...and convert her to Christianity.
劝她改信基督教
That's as much mischief as you're allowed.
只准乱来到这种程度
Come, let's find a quiet corner.
我们找个安静的地方
Now, you forget about your practice.
别管开业的事了
You have other things to do.
你还有别的事要做
India has many men with too much wealth.
印度有很多有钱人
And it's their privilege to nourish the effort of the few...
能培养一些使印度不再冷漠
...who can raise India from servitude and apathy.
并脱离奴役的人是他们的荣幸
I'll see to it.
我会办到的
You begin your journal.
你办你的杂志吧
I have little to say.
我没什么好说的
Come, let's sit down.
坐下吧
India is an alien country to me.
印度对我而言是外国
Change that.
改变这种想法
Go and find India.
去找寻印度
Not what you see here...
不是你在这里看到的
...but the real India.
而是真正的印度
You'll see what needs to be said...
那你就会知道有什么需要说
...what we need to hear.
知道我们需要听些什么
When I saw you in that tunic, I knew.
我一看到你穿着这身装扮 我就知道
I knew I could die in peace.
我就知道自己可以瞑目了
Make India proud of herself.
让印度能足以自豪
Charlie, please. You're both being foolish.
查理，你们两个别傻了
But the air is lovely. Anyway, there's no room in there.
可是空气好棒 何况里面也没位子了
Please. Come in.
拜托你们进来…
No violence, please.
请别使用暴力
Let me hang on with two hands or I will fall.
让我用两只手抓 不然我会摔下去的
Englishman-sahib!
英国人，大人
Come, there is room up here!
上面有座位
Put your foot on the window.
踩着窗户
Come!
来！
- What are you doing? - I'm going nearer to God.
-你在做什么 -接近上帝
Charlie! Be careful!
查理，小心
Let go!
放手
- Let go! - Oh, dear!
-放手 -老天
Hello.
哈罗
You see? It is most comfortable.
看吧，这里最舒服了
Sahib?
大人
Are you a Christian?
你是基督徒吗？
Yes, I'm a Christian.
是的…我是基督徒
I know a Christian.
我认识一个基督徒
She drinks blood.
她喝血
Blood of Christ, every Sunday.
每个星期日都喝基督的血
Charlie!
查理
It's all right, sahib. It's very safe.
没关系，大人，很安全的
Bend!
弯下来
Pray to God, sahib.
祷告吧
Now is when it is best to be Hindu.
现在你最好能是个印度徒
I agree with Jinnah.
我同意吉纳的看法
Now that the Americans are in, the war will be over soon.
美国既然参战了 战争马上就会结束
The Germans are worn out as it is.
德国已经元气大伤
And our first act should be...
我们首先应该
...to convene a congress party convention...
组织国会
...and demand independence.
要求独立
And we will speak with one voice.
要同声一气
United.
团结一致
And we should invite Gandhi.
并且要邀请甘地参加
What the devil's happened to him?
他到底怎么了
He's discovering India.
他去找寻印度了
A lot better than making trouble where it matters!
这样比在重要事物上惹麻烦 要好的多了
Invite him, let him say his piece about South Africa...
邀请他参加 让他说说他在南非的事迹
...then let him slip into oblivion.
然后让他被遗忘吧
Insurgents.
暴徒
They've derailed a troop train.
他们让运兵车脱轨了
Keep clear! Come on.
走开！ 快
They've killed an English soldier.
他们杀了一个英国士兵
We were asked for toleration.
他们要求我们容忍
We were asked for patience.
要求我们忍耐
Some of us gave it...
我们有些人做到了
...and some did not.
但是有些人做不到
Their war is over.
现在他们的战争已经结束了
And those of us who supported it...
不论支持
...and those of us who refused...
或不支持的人
...must forget our differences.
都应该忘掉所有的歧见
And there can be no excuses...
现在英国
...from the British now.
不能再有藉口了
India wants...
印度需要
...home rule.
自治
India...
印度
...demands home rule!
要求自治
Congratulations.
恭喜
And let no one question...
不要心存疑问
...that Mr. Jinnah speaks...
吉纳先生所说的不仅
...not just for the Muslims...
代表回教徒
...but for all India!
也代表印度教徒
And now...
现在
...l'm going to introduce to you...
我要介绍一位人士
...a man whose writings...
他的文章
...we are all becoming familiar with.
大家已经逐渐熟悉
A man who stood in high esteem with our own beloved Gokhale.
他是我们挚爱的哥汉 极为敬重的一个人
A man whose accomplishments...
他在南非的成就 将永远难以磨灭
Mr. Mohandas Gandhi!
甘地先生
Your journal has made great impact.
你的杂志引起极大的回响
I'm flattered by Mr. Patel.
彼帖先生太过奖了
I would be even more flattered if what he said were true.
如果说的是真的 我就更受宠若惊了
But it is true.
是真的
I read it. Often!
我常读的
Since I returned from South Africa...
自从我回国后
...I have traveled over much of India.
就一直在印度到处旅行
And I know that I could travel for many more years...
我知道即使再旅行几年
...and still only see a small part of her.
我也只能看到印度的一小部份
And yet, I already know...
不过我已经能了解
...that what we say here...
我们在这里所说的一切
...means nothing to the masses of our country.
对大多数的同胞而言毫无意义
Here, we make speeches for each other...
在这里，我们互相给那些 可能刊登我们意见的
...and those English liberal magazines that may grant us a few lines.
那些英国自由解放杂志 发表演说
But the people of India...
可是对印度人民而言
...are...
却是
...untouched.
言不及意
Their politics are confined to bread...
他们的政治只限于面包
...and salt.
和盐
Illiterate they may be, but they're not blind.
我们或许是文盲 但是眼睛并没瞎
They see no reason to give their loyalty to rich and powerful men...
他们没有理由 效忠有权有势的人
...who simply want to take over the role of the British...
这些人只是在藉自由之名
...in the name of freedom.
趁机取英国而代之
This congress tells the world...
这个国会向世界宣布
...it represents India.
说他们代表印度
My brothers...
兄弟们
...lndia...
印度
...is 700,000 villages...
有70万个村落
...not a few hundred lawyers in Delhi...
不是只有在新德里和孟买的
...and Bombay.
几百个律师
Until we stand in the fields...
除非我们和那些
...with the millions that toil each day under the hot sun...
顶着烈日 做苦工的多数同胞同甘共苦
...we will not represent India.
否则我们就不能代表印度
Nor will we ever be able to challenge the British...
也不能以国家之名
...as one nation.
来对抗英国
Have you read his magazine?
你看过他的杂志吗
No.
没有
But I think I'm going to.
不过我想我会要看了
Pull over.
靠边停
This can't be the way.
一定走错了
Yes, I'm sure this is the direction India is taking.
是的 我想印度将朝这方面迈进
To think I almost got excited by Mr. Jinnah...
想到自己听了吉纳的话 就几乎激动起来
...when all this was awaiting me.
居然还有更精彩的在后头
We're looking for Mr. Gandhi.
我们在找甘地先生
- You'll find him under that tree. - Thank you.
-你可以在那棵树下找到他 -谢谢
I'm anxious to meet this new force.
快点，我急着要看看这新力量
I try to live like an Indian, as you see.
我努力地像个印度人生活
It's stupid, of course.
这当然很蠢
Because in our country...
因为在印度
...it is the British who decide how an Indian lives...
是英国人 决定印度人的生活方式
...what he may buy, what he may sell.
能够买什么，能够卖什么
And from their luxury...
从他们的富有
...in the midst of...
我们的贫苦中
...our terrible poverty...
他们还要告诉我们
...they instruct us on what is justice, what is sedition.
何为公理 何为妨害治安
So it's only natural that our best young minds...
所以难怪我们顶尖的年轻人
...assume an air of Eastern dignity...
虽然有东方的尊贵气质
...while greedily assimilating...
却一碰到西方的弱点
...every Western weakness as quickly as they can acquire it.
就毫无抵抗的与其同化
If we have home rule...
只要能自治
...that'll change.
那就会改变
Would you, please?
请帮我拿
Why should the British grant us home rule?
英国为什么要准我们自治
Here, we must take the peelings to the goats.
把这个果皮拿给羊吃
We only make wild speeches or perform even wilder acts of terrorism.
我们只能口出狂言 做出恐怖的事情
We've bred an army of anarchists...
养了一批无政府主义的军队
...but not one single group that can really fight the British anywhere.
但与英国对抗时就全溃不成军
But I thought you were against fighting.
我以为你们是反对战斗的
Now...
现在
...just spread it around.
散开在地上
There you are.
好了
They like the new peelings mixed in with the rotting ones.
它们喜欢 新旧果皮混在一起吃
Where there's injustice, I always believed in fighting.
只要有不公正的事 我一向主张要战斗
The question is, do you fight to change things or to punish?
问题是你是为改变事物而战 还是为惩罚而战
I've found we're all such sinners we should leave punishment to God.
我自己则是认为人类都是罪人 这种惩罚的事应该交给上帝
And if we really want to change things...
如果想改变事物
...there are better ways of doing it...
有很多方法
...than derailing trains or slashing someone with a sword.
比让火车出轨和杀人好
The fire is ready.
火升好了
You see...
你看
...even here...
就算在这里
...we live under tyranny.
也有暴政
What did I tell you?
我说过吧
Look at him!
看看他
I can see the British shaking now.
我可以看见英国在发抖了
I'm looking for Mr. Gandhi.
我来找甘地先生
I've been trying to speak to you for a long time.
我一直想跟你说话
Our crops.
我们卖不出
We cannot sell them.
我们的收成
We have no money.
我们没钱
But the landlords still demand the same rent.
可是地主不肯减地租
We have nothing left.
我们一无所有了
Mr. Taylor, sir.
泰勒先生
Up here!
这边
Jesus.
天啊
What the hell is going on?
这里到底发生了什么事
I don't know, sir.
我不知道
The agent got a telegram.
站长收到一封电报
And it just said, "He is coming" and gave the time of the train.
上面只说他来了 和说明火车到站的时间
Who the hell is "he"?
他是谁
I don't know, sir.
我不知道，长官
Make way!
让开…
Out of the way. Come on, you!
走开，就是你
Who the devil are you?
你是谁
My name is Mohandas K. Gandhi.
我叫做莫罕德甘地
Whoever you are, we don't want you here.
我不管你是谁，我们不要你来
I suggest you get back on that train before it leaves.
我建议你马上坐这班火车回去
They seem to want me.
他们似乎要我来
Now, look here.
你给我听着
I'll put you under arrest, if you'd prefer.
你是宁可要被逮捕吗
On what charge?
什么罪名
I don't want any trouble.
我不希望出事
I'm an Indian traveling in my own country.
我是个印度人 在自己的国家里旅行
I see no reason for trouble.
会惹出什么事
Well, there had better not be.
最好别惹事
Make way for the officer.
让开…
For years...
多年来
...the landlords have ordered us...
地主一直命令我们
...to grow indigo...
种靛青树
...for dyeing cloth.
用来染布料
Always, they took part of the crop as rent.
以一部份收成为租金
But now...
可是现在
...everyone buys their cloth from England.
大家都跟英国买布料
So no one wants...
没有人要
...our indigo.
我们的靛青染料
The landlords...
地主们
...say we must pay our rent...
要我们用现金
...in cash.
付租金
What we could...
我们能卖的
...we sold.
都卖了
The police have taken the rest.
剩下的被警察拿走了
There is...
我们
...no food.
没吃的了
I understand.
我明白了
The landlords are British?
地主都是英国人
What we can do, we will try to do.
我们会尽量设法去解决
Shukla...
苏克拉
...is all Champaran like this?
整个占婆兰省都这样吗
Yes, Bapu.
是的，巴布
The whole region.
全部
Hundreds.
成千
Thousands.
上万的人
Some landlords have tried to help.
有些地主想帮忙
But what can they do?
但是他们又能做什么呢
Are you Mr. M. K. Gandhi?
你是甘地先生吗
I'm sorry, you're under arrest.
对不起，你被捕了
I'm not sorry at all.
我一点也不难过
Who did you say would be buying the drinks?
你说谁要请喝酒的
Oh, no!
不会吧！
Wouldn't you know, that's the best innings I've had since Oxford.
你知道吗，这是从牛津毕业后 最棒的一场球赛
India's full of grief, old man.
印度到处都是愁苦的老人
I've got no idea.
我完全不知道
All I know is there's a riot or something at Motihari in Champaran.
只知道占婆兰省提哈利 有暴动还是什么的
The whole company's ordered out.
全营都奉令要出动
I would like to see the prisoner.
我想见犯人
On the left, sir.
在左边
Shades of South Africa.
南非模式
Not quite.
不尽然
They're only holding me...
现在只是拘留
...until the magistrate's hearing.
要到本县县长审问后
Then it will be prison.
才是坐牢
Did they take your clothes?
他们拿走你的衣物了
These are my clothes now.
现在起我的衣服就是这些了
You always had a puritanical streak.
你一向有清教徒的倾向
If I want to be one with them...
如果想成为他们的一份子
...I have to live like them.
就必须和他们一样的生活
Yes, I think you do.
我想你是想
But thank God we all don't.
感谢上帝 不是所有的人都这样
My puritanism runs in a different way.
我的清教门派跟你的方向不同
I'm far too modest for such a display.
我没胆量穿成这种装扮
Couldn't I be let in with the prisoner? I am a clergyman.
能不能让我进去，我是神父
They're calling you "Bapu."
他们叫你“巴布”
I thought it meant "father."
我以为那是指父亲
It does.
是这个意思
We must be getting old, Charlie.
我们一定都老了
What do you want me to do?
你要我为你做什么
I think that you can help us most...
可以帮忙的就是
...by taking that assignment you've been offered in Fiji.
接受在斐济那个职务
I have to be sure...
我必须要确定
They have to be sure that what we do...
他们也一样 这件事我们印度人
...can be done by Indians alone.
自己就能办得到
But you know the strategy.
可是你懂我们的策略
The world is full of people who will despise what's happening here.
世界上有很多人也不屑 英国在这里的一切行为
It is their strength that we need.
我们需要的 就是这些人的力量
Before you go...
在你走之前
...you could start us in the right direction.
可以先指引我们正确的方向
I must leave from Calcutta...
我得由加尔各答离境
...and soon.
而且要很快地走
Say goodbye to Ba for me.
你必须替我跟芭说再见
Well, I...
那我…
There are no goodbyes for us.
我们之间不用道别
Wherever you are, you will always be in my heart.
不论你人在哪里 在我心里永远都会有你
I'm going to clear the courtroom.
我要清场
I'm not sure we'd be able to.
我不知道我们能清场吗
It is a first hearing. It's supposed to be public.
这是初审，应该是公开的
And he's a lawyer.
而且他是律师
I don't know where they found the nerve.
我不知道他们哪来的胆子
I don't either, but the troops won't be here till tomorrow.
我也不知道 可是军队明天才会到
How did the press get here before the military?
新闻记者怎么会比军队早来的
That English clergyman sent a number of telegrams yesterday.
那个英国神父昨天下午 发了封电报出去
I understand one of them even went to the Viceroy.
我知道其中有一封是给总督的
You have been ordered out of the province...
本庭宣判你扰乱治安之罪
...on the grounds of disturbing the peace.
驱逐出境
With respect, I refuse to go.
我拒绝离境
Do you want to go to jail?
你想坐牢吗
As you wish.
随便你
All right.
好吧
I will release you on bail...
只要一百卢比交保
...of 100 rupees until I reach a sentence.
我就释放你直到判刑确定
I refuse to pay 100 rupees.
我拒绝缴一百卢比的保释金
Then I will grant release on bail...
那就无罪开释
...without payment until I reach a decision.
直到我做决定为止
Gandhiji! Gandhiji!
甘地…
We are from Bihar.
我们是从比哈来的
We received a cable from an old friend...
早上我们接到一封
...who was at Cambridge with us.
剑桥老友的电报
His name is Nehru.
他叫尼鲁
- I believe you know him. - Indeed.
-我想你认识他 -是的
He tells us you need help, and we have come to give it.
他说你需要帮助 所以我们就来了
I want to document coldly, rationally, what is being done here.
我要记录这里的一切 要冷静而理性的
It may take months.
可能要费时好几个月
We have no pressing engagements.
我们目前没什么事
You will have to live with the peasants.
你们必须和佃农在一起
There will be risks.
会有危险性
I don't know what this country is coming to.
真搞不懂这个国家是怎么了
But good God, man!
老天啊！
You yourself raised the rent simply to finance a hunting expedition.
可是你为了一次狩猎的花费 就要提高租金
And some of these others: Beatings, illegal seizures...
还有其他的事情 例如殴打，非法拘捕
...demanding services without pay.
强迫他们为你工作却不给薪水
Even refusing them water.
甚至拒绝给他们水喝
In India!
在印度
Nobody knows what it is to try to get these people to work.
不知道要怎么样 才能叫这些印度人工作
You've made this half-naked whatever-he-is...
你让这个半裸的砘
...into an international hero.
变成世界闻名的英雄
"One lone man, marching dusty roads, armed only with honesty...
孤单一人手持竹竿 在朴朴风尘中仅以诚实为武器
...and a bamboo staff, doing battle with the British Empire."
与大英帝国孤军奋战
At home, children are writing essays about him.
在英国 孩子们都以他为作文题目
What do they want?
他们要什么
Gareth!
盖勒
There's a rebate on rents paid.
租金减少
They're to be free to grow crops of their own choice.
准许他们自由栽种作物
And a commission, part Indian, to hear grievances.
一个由英国人和印度人组成的 民怨处理委员会
That would satisfy him?
这该能让他满意了
And His Majesty's government.
英王的政府也会满意
It only needs your signature for the landlords.
只要你签个字给地主
It'll be worth it to see the back of him.
只要能赶走他就值得了
Thank you, sir.
谢谢长官
We're too damned liberal.
我们太过放任了
Perhaps.
或许
At least this has made the government see some sense about what men...
不过至少能让政府了解
...like Mr. Gandhi should be allowed and denied.
对甘地这类人 该准他什么，不准他什么
Where is Mr. Gandhi?
甘地先生呢
He said he preferred to walk, sir.
他说他宁愿走路
I followed him most of the way. He's just turned the corner.
我一路跟着他 他就在转角
He came third class.
他坐三等车厢来的
God, give me patience.
神请赐予我耐心
My house is honored.
真是蓬壁生辉
The honor is ours.
是我们的荣幸
I'd like you to meet Dr. Kallenbach, an old friend.
这是可朗北先生 是我的老朋友
His interest is in flowers.
他对花很有兴趣
I told him he could wander your garden while we talked.
我擅自作主告诉他说 我们说话时他可以去花园走走
I'll send for my gardener. You'll have plenty to discuss.
我会叫我的园丁来 我想你们有很多话可以聊
Thank you.
谢谢
Gentleman, the hero of Champaran.
各位，占婆兰的英雄
Only the stubborn man of Champaran.
我只是占婆兰的一个老顽固
Mr. Patel you know.
你认识彼帖先生
Maulana Azad, my colleague and a fellow Muslim...
马拉纳尔塞，我的同僚 也是个回教徒
...and just recently released from prison.
他最近才出狱
Adab.
你好
Mr. Kripalani.
克力帕先生
And of course, you know Mr. Nehru.
当然，你认识尼鲁先生
I'm beginning to know Mr. Nehru.
我开始认识尼鲁先生了
Please sit down.
请坐
Gentlemen, I've asked you to come here through Mr. Jinnah's kindness...
各位，我透过吉纳先生 邀请各位来这里
...because I've had the chance to see the legislation.
因为本人有幸看到法案原文
And it is exactly as was rumored.
一切诚如谣传
Arrest without warrant, and automatic imprisonment...
逮捕不需要拘捕状
...for possession of materials considered seditious.
若拥有其视为妨害治安的书刊 立即拘捕坐牢
And your writings are specifically listed.
你写的文章被点名列出来
So much for helping them in the Great War.
帮他们打世界大仗等于白打了
There is only one answer: Direct action on a scale...
只有一条路，直接行动
...they can never handle.
规模要大到让他们措手不及
I don't think so.
我认为不妥
Terrorism would only justify their repression.
恐怖主义正是 出兵镇压的好理由
And what kind of leaders would it throw up?
而且这样会造就出 什么样的领导者
Are they men that we would want at the head of our country?
我们需要这种人来领导本国吗
I too have read Mr. Gandhi's writings...
我也读过甘地先生的文章
...but I'd rather be ruled by an Indian terrorist than an English one.
但我宁可让印度的恐怖份子统治 也不要英国人
And I don't intend to submit to that kind of law.
我绝不屈服于此法之下
I must say, it seems to me...
我觉得问题太严重
...that it's gone beyond remedies like passive resistance.
消极的抵抗无效
If I may...
而我…
...l, for one, have never advocated passive anything.
我本人从未提倡消极抵抗
I'm with Mr. Jinnah.
我赞成吉纳先生
We must never submit to such laws...
我们绝对不向此法屈服
...ever.
绝不
And I think our resistance must be active and provocative.
我觉得我们的反抗 应该积极的富煽动性
May I?
能不能让我来
I want to embarrass all those who wish to treat us as slaves.
我要让那些 想奴役我们的人难为情
Thank you.
谢谢你
All of them.
他们全部的人
- Forgive my stupid illustration. - Allow me.
-这是个愚昧的例子 -我来
No, please.
不了
But I want to change their minds...
但是我要改变他们的心灵
...not kill them for weaknesses we all possess.
而不是杀他们，就因为 他们具有和我们一样的弱点
And what resistance would you offer?
你建议要用何种的抵抗
The law is due to take effect from April 6.
此法将于4月6日生效
I want to call upon the nation...
我要号召全国人民在当天
...to make that a day of prayer and fasting.
全体祷告和绝食
A general strike?
你是指全面性罢工
I mean a day of prayer and fasting.
我是说祷告和绝食
Of course, no work could be done. No buses.
当然不工作，巴士
No trains.
火车都停开
No factories.
工厂停工
No administration.
政府不办公
The country would stop.
全国停摆
My God, it would terrify them!
天啊，他们一定会吓坏的
350 million people at prayer?
三亿五千人都在祷告
Even the English newspapers would have to report that...
即使是英国报纸也非得报导
...and explain why.
并要解释原因
- But could we get people to do it? - Why not?
-可是我们做得到吗 -怎么会做不到
Champaran stirred the whole country.
占婆兰事件敲醒全国
Thank you.
谢谢
They're calling you "Mahatma."
他们叫你“圣雄”
"Great Soul."
伟大的灵魂
Fortunately, such news comes very slowly to where I live.
还好这种消息都很慢 才会传到我们的村子
I think if we all worked to publicize it...
我想如果大家都努力宣传
...all of Congress...
所有的国会议员
...every avenue we know...
在街头巷尾加以宣传
I could get articles printed in most of the papers in Delhi and Bombay.
我能叫新德里和孟买的 多数报纸刊载此事
Only civilians will visit. Don't you think so, Your Highness?
只有平民会到，不是吗，陛下？
Of course, the army will always be loyal.
当然，军队会效忠的
I'll have you know, we've got 500 troops.
你们要知道，我们的军力雄厚
Damn hungry by morning. I'll tell you that.
我告诉你，到早上就会饿了
Excuse me, Your Excellency.
对不起，大人
Mr. Kinnoch.
金诺先生来了
Sir, I'm afraid it's confirmed.
恐怕已经证实了
Nothing's working, sir.
一切都停工了
The buses, the train, the markets.
巴士，火车，市场
There's not even any ordinary civilian staff here, sir.
这里的平民职员也没来上班
Is it simply Delhi and Bombay?
只有新德里和孟买吗
Karachi, Calcutta, Madras, Bangalore. It's total.
喀拉蚩，加尔各答，穆德拉斯 邦加罗尔，是全国性的
The army had to take over the telegraph...
军队只好接管电报局
...or we'd be cut off from the world.
否则我们会与世界失去联系
I can't believe it.
真是不敢相信
He's going to sell his own paper tomorrow in Bombay, sir.
他办的报纸 明天将在孟买开始发行
They've called for a parade on Victoria Road.
他们要在维多利亚路上游行
Arrest him.
逮捕他
He's to go to the visitors' room.
带他去会客室
Bapu.
巴布
You too?
你也…
It seems less formal than Mahatma.
较“圣雄”亲切
Since your arrest, the riots have hardly stopped.
自从你被逮捕后 暴动一直都没停过
Not big, but they keep breaking out.
规模不大，不过一直不断爆发
I run to stop them.
我忙着制止
And Patel and Kripalani, they're never at rest.
彼帖和克利帕也没停过
But some English civilians have been killed.
但是已经有些英国平民被杀了
And the army is attacking crowds with clubs.
英军用木棒攻击群众
Sometimes worse.
有时候更糟
Maybe I'm wrong.
或许我错了
Maybe we're not ready yet.
或许印度人还没准备好
In South Africa, our numbers were small.
在南非，我们人数少
The government's afraid. They don't know what to do.
政府很害怕 不知道该如何是好
They're more afraid of terrorism than of you.
他们害怕你 但是更怕恐怖主义
The Viceroy has agreed to your release, if you will speak for nonviolence.
总督同意只要你肯出面 主张不用暴力就释放你
I've never spoken for anything else.
我从来没有主张过暴力
England...
大英帝国
...is so powerful.
是如此强大
Its army...
陆军
...and its navy...
海军
...all its modern weapons...
全配备着现代武器
But when a great power like that...
但是当他们用如此强大的武力
...strikes defenseless people...
来对付无抵抗力的人民时
...it shows its brutality...
就显示出他们的残酷，不仁道
...its own weakness.
也暴露他们的弱点
Especially when those people do not strike back.
尤其是当那些人不还击时
Fighting back will not work.
还击是没有用的
And that is why the Mahatma...
所以圣雄
...begs us to take the course of nonviolence.
才要求我们非暴力的行动
Back away!
退后…
But if we riot...
如果我们暴动
...if we fight back...
如果还击
...we become the vandals...
我们就成为破坏者
...and they become the law.
他们就成为合法者
If we bear their blows, they are the vandals.
如果我们承受攻击 他们就是破坏者
God and His law are on our...
神与法律就站在我们这边
Front rank, kneel in position!
第一班采跪姿
We...
我们
...must have the courage...
一定要有承受
...to take their anger.
其愤怒的勇气
Should we issue a warning, sir?
我们要先警告他们吗
They've had their warning:
我们已经警告过了
No meetings.
不准集会
Fire!
开枪…
Take your time!
慢慢来
Corporal!
下士
To your left.
向左方射击
General Dyer...
戴尔将军
...is it correct that you ordered your troops to fire...
你是否曾叫部队
...at the thickest part of the crowd?
往人最多的地方射击
That is so.
是的
1,516 casualties with...
死伤1516个人
...1,650 bullets.
用了1650发子弹
My intention was to inflict a lesson...
我是想杀鸡儆猴
...that would have an impact throughout all India.
让全印度人都能有所警惕
General...
将军
...had you been able to take in the armored car...
如果你能把装甲车开进去
...would you have opened fire with the machine gun?
你会用机关枪来扫射吗
I think, probably, yes.
我想可能会吧
General, did you realize there were children and women in the crowd?
将军，你知道群众里有妇孺吗
I did.
我知道
But that was irrelevant to the point you were making?
可是为了达到目的 这都无关紧要吗
That is correct.
是的
Could I ask you what provision you made for the wounded?
能不能请问你如何处置伤者
I was ready to help any who applied.
只要申请救援都予以救助
General, how does a child...
将军
...shot with a.303 Lee-Enfield...
一个中弹的小孩
...apply for help?
如何来求救呢
Forgive me, gentlemen, but you must understand...
请原谅我 不过你们必须了解
...that His Majesty's government and the British people repudiate...
国王陛下的政府和英国人民
...both the massacre and the philosophy that prompted it.
否认此次大屠杀的发生及其原因
Now...
现在
...what I would like to do...
我想对此新立法
...is to come to some compromise...
采取一个
...over the new...
折衷方案
If you will excuse me, Your Excellency...
请容我插嘴，大人
...it is our view that matters have gone beyond legislation.
在我们看来 此事已经不仅关乎“立法”
We think it is time you recognized...
我们觉得贵国政府该体认到
...that you are masters in someone else's home.
你们是在别人家里当主人
Despite the best intentions of the best of you...
不论你们有多好心
...you must, in the nature of things, humiliate us to control us.
你们必须羞辱我们才能控制我们
General Dyer is but an extreme example of the principle.
戴尔将军只是这种理念下 一个极端的例子
It is time you left.
是该你们离去的时候了
With respect, Mr. Gandhi...
甘地先生
...without British administration...
没有英国的统治
...this country would be reduced to chaos.
印度会大乱的
Mr. Kinnoch...
奇诺先生
...I beg you to accept that there is no people...
请你接受这个事实 世界上任何人
...who would not prefer their own bad government...
都宁可要一个自己的坏政府
...to the good government of an alien power.
也不要外国的好政府
My dear sir, India is British.
印度是英国的属地
We're hardly an alien power.
我们并非是外国
Even if His Majesty could waive all other considerations...
即使国王陛下 能放下一切顾虑
...he has a duty to the millions of his Muslim subjects...
国王对印度上百万的回教国民 负有责任
...who are a minority in this realm.
在此其为少数
And experience suggests that his troops...
过去的经验显示维持和平
...and his administration are essential...
必须用上英王的军队
...in order to secure the peace.
以及统治方式
All nations contain religious minorities.
各国都有某教派的少数份子
Like other countries, ours will have its problems.
就如其他国家也会有这种问题
But they will be ours...
但这是我们的问题
...not yours.
而不是你们的
How do you propose to make them yours?
你要如何使它变成你们的
You don't think we're just going to walk out of India?
你认为我们会就这样走出印度吗？
Yes.
是的
In the end...
到最后
...you will walk out...
你们总是要走出去
...because 100,000 Englishmen simply cannot control...
因为凭十万的英国人是
...350 million Indians, if those Indians refuse...
无法控制三亿五千万个印度人
...to cooperate.
如果印度人不合作的话
And that is what we intend to achieve.
这正是我们的目的
Peaceful, nonviolent noncooperation...
和平的，不使用暴力的，不合作
...till you yourself see the wisdom of leaving...
直到你们自己 能够明智的撤走
...Your Excellency.
大人
I said to him, "You don't expect us just to walk out?"
我问他，你认为我们 会就这样走出去
And he said, "Yes."
他说，是的
What an extraordinary little man, isn't he?
他真是个了不起的小个子
"Nonviolence, noncooperation."
不用暴力，不合作
For a moment, I was afraid they were actually going to do something.
我原本担心 他们真的要有所行动
Yes, but I think it would be wise to be very cautious for a time.
不过我认为还是得小心一点
The Antiterrorist Act will remain on the statutes.
反恐怖行动仍在政法中
But on no account is Gandhi to be arrested.
不过不能逮捕甘地
Whatever mischief he causes...
不管他造成了多大的灾害
...I have no intention of making a martyr of him.
我可不想把他捧成殉难者
But now something worse is happening.
可是现在情况更糟了
When Gandhiji and I were growing up...
在甘地和我还小的时候
...women wove their own cloth.
女人自己织布自己穿
But now there are millions who have no work...
可是现在上百万个人失业了
...because those who can buy all they need from England.
因为买得起的人 都向英国购买一切所需
I say with Gandhiji:
我和甘地都觉得
There is no beauty in the finest cloth...
如果最漂亮的布匹
...if it makes hunger and unhappiness.
会造成饥饿和不幸 便不再漂亮了
My message to you...
我要对你们所说的
...is the message I have given to your brothers everywhere.
就如我对其他同胞说的一样
To gain independence...
想要独立自主
...we must prove worthy of it.
必须先证明自己，才能够独立
There must be Hindu-Muslim unity always.
印度教与回教必须 一直团结下去
Second...
第二
...no Indian must be treated as the English treat us.
英国人所对待我们的方式 绝不能也对待于印度同胞身上
We must remove untouchability...
必须从心中和实际生活中
...from our hearts and from our lives.
除去低等贱民的观念
Third...
第三
...we must defy the British.
必须反抗英国人
Not with violence that will inflame their will...
不是使用暴力 那会激怒他们
...but with a firmness that will open their eyes.
而是以坚定的态度 才能使其张开双眼
English factories make the cloth...
制造衣服的英国工厂
...that makes our poverty.
使我们贫穷
All those who wish to make the English see...
要让英国人明白
...bring me the cloth from Manchester and Leeds that you wear today...
把英国制衣服交给我
...and we will light a fire that will be seen in Delhi...
让我们烧了它们，让新德里
...and in London.
和伦敦都能看到这个光芒
And if...
如果
...like me...
像我一样
...you are left with only one piece of homespun...
你们只剩一件手织衣物可穿
...wear it with dignity.
那就神气的穿着它
Thank you very much.
非常谢谢
No, thank you, I can manage.
不，谢谢你，我来拿
Don't destroy my good intentions.
贺曼，别扰我的兴了
I'm already feeling guilty about traveling second class.
我坐二等舱已经很内疚了
You've earned a few indulgences.
这些小享受是你用努力赚来的
Perhaps, but Maulana's made of sterner stuff.
但，莫拉纳比我更坚强
Our trains met in Bombay.
我们的火车在孟买相遇
And there he is, back there in that lot. The model disciple.
我看到他坐在后面 真是个模范门徒
There's another passenger.
还有另一个乘客
A Miss Slade from London. She's been writing to Gandhiji for years.
伦敦来的丝蕾蒂小姐 她和甘地通信了好几年
She's the daughter of an English admiral.
她是英国海军上将的女儿
What do you think the daughter of an English admiral...
一个英国海军上将的女儿
...proposes to do in our ashram?
去我们的阿思朗做什么
Sink us?
把我们弄沉吗
From the looks of the luggage, yes.
看她有那么多行李，很像
She wants to make her home with us.
她想和我们同居共事
And Gandhiji has agreed.
甘地答应了
Miss Slade!
丝蕾蒂小姐
You'd be Mr. Kallenbach.
你一定是可朗北先生
And you would be Miss Slade?
你是丝蕾蒂小姐吗
I prefer the name Gandhiji has given me:
我喜欢甘地大师 帮我取的名字
Mirabehn.
米乐曼
Don't pull it so fast.
别拉这么快
You'll break it again.
又会弄断的
Leave it.
别弄了
God gave you ten thumbs.
上帝给你十根大姆指
Eleven.
十一根
Sardar!
沙达
Mirabehn!
米乐曼
Come, come.
别这样…
You will be my daughter.
你以后就是我的女儿了
But then...
但是…
...some rioting broke out...
有些暴动
...between Hindus and Muslims.
是教派之间的
Violent, terrible.
又粗暴，又可怕
Whether it was provoked...
是否有人蓄意煽动
...I don't know.
我不知道
But it gave them an excuse to impose martial law throughout Bengal.
可是英方有藉口 在孟加拉实施戒严了
Some of the things the military have done...
军队的一些作为…
Is the campaign weakening?
不合作运动减弱了吗
The marches and protests are bigger, if anything.
游行和抗议都空前的盛大
But with the censorship here...
可是出版物检查严格
...they know more in England...
英国那边
...than we do.
都比我们知道的多
It saps the courage...
单独受苦之念
...to think you may be suffering alone.
削弱勇气
They are not alone.
我们不孤单
And martial law only shows how desperate the British are.
戒严就是证明 英方在做困兽之斗
Is that homespun?
是手织布吗
I sent for it from here.
我叫人由这里带去
I dyed it myself.
我自己染的颜色
What do the workers in England make of what we're doing?
英国的劳动者 对我们的运动有什么想法
It must have produced hardship.
一定使他们很辛苦
It has...
是的
...but you'd be surprised. They really do understand.
可是你一定很异 他们了解，真的了解
Good.
很好
Ba will have to teach you to spin too.
芭也会教你织布
- I'd rather march. - First, spin!
-我宁愿去游行 -先学织布
Let the others march for a time.
让别人去游行一下
I'll teach you all our foolishness.
我会把我们的傻玩意教给你
And you must teach me yours.
你也要教我你们的东西
We burn British cloth!
我们烧掉英国衣服…
Long live Gandhiji!
甘地万岁…
British rule must go!
英国滚蛋…
I'll stuff it down your damn throat!
我要把这个塞进你的喉咙
Help us!
救命…
Leave us alone! We're not harming you.
别这样，我们又没有伤害你
Go on your way!
走吧…
Come back!
回来！
Help us!
救命…
That's one bit of news they haven't censored.
他们可没禁止这则新闻
Now it's all over the world.
全世界都知道
India's nonviolence.
印度的“非暴力”
What can we do?
我们该怎么办
We must end the campaign.
我们必须停止这个运动
After what they did at the massacre? It's only an eye for an eye.
英军屠杀我们 如此也只算以眼还眼
An eye for an eye only ends up making the whole world blind.
以眼还眼 只会使整个世界都盲目
Do you know the sacrifices people have made?
可是你可知道我们所做的牺牲
We would never get the same commitment again, ever.
我们再也无法重获支持
The whole of India is on the move!
全印度都投入这个运动
Yes, but in what direction?
是的，可是是以哪种方向
If we obtain our freedom by murder and bloodshed, I want no part of it.
如果我们用谋杀流血 来得到自由，我宁可不要
You are the father of the nation.
你是印度的国父
Today, I see no ground in that for anything but shame.
今天这个称呼 只会让我觉得羞愧
It was one incident.
只是一次意外
Tell that to the families of the policemen who died.
去告诉那些死难警察的家人
The whole nation is marching.
全国都在游行
They wouldn't stop even if we asked them to.
即使叫他们停也不会停的
I will ask.
我来求他们
And I will fast as a penance for my part in arousing such emotions.
而且我要绝食 以忏悔自己挑动此情绪
And I will not stop until they stop.
他们停止我才停止绝食
But...
可是…
God! You can be sure the British won't censor that.
天啊，英方一定 不会禁止刊登这个消息
They'll put it on every street corner.
大街小巷到处宣传
People are aroused.
人们既然已经起而投入
They won't stop!
他们就不会停的
If I die, perhaps they will stop.
如果我死了 或许他们就会停止
I must get ready for morning prayers.
我得去准备晨祷了
Mirabehn is here.
米乐曼来了
I've brought your drinking water.
我拿了些开水来
There's a little lemon juice in it.
只是加了一点柠檬汁
That's all.
就这样
Herman has gone to meet Pandit Nehru.
贺曼去见尼鲁了
There was a telegram.
有电报来说
Almost everywhere, it has stopped.
几乎全部停止了
When it is everywhere...
全部停止时
...then my prayers will be answered.
神才算听到我的祷告
Do you find me stubborn?
你觉得我很顽固
I don't know.
我不知道
I know that you are right.
我知道你是对的
I don't know that this is right.
却不知道这样做对吗
May I turn you?
我帮你翻身好吗
When I despair...
当我绝望时
...I remember that all through history...
会想起在历史上
...the way of truth and love has always won.
只有真理和爱能得胜
There have been tyrants and murderers...
历史上有很多暴君和凶手
...and, for a time, they can seem invincible.
在短期内或许是所向无敌的
But in the end, they always fall.
但是终就总是会失败
Think of it.
好好想一想
Always.
永远如此
Whenever you are in doubt that that is God's way...
当你怀疑神
...the way the world is meant to be...
怀疑这世界时
...think of that...
就想想这些话
...and then try to do it His way.
然后努力以神的方式去做
And now, could I have another feast of lemon juice?
能不能再给我一杯柠檬汁
Panditji!
尼鲁
Jinnah...
吉纳
...Patel...
彼帖
...all of congress has called for the end of noncooperation.
所有的国会议会都起而呼吁 停止不合作运动
There's not been one demonstration.
没有示威了
All over India, people are praying that you will end the fast.
所有的印度人都在祈祷 希望你结束绝食
They're walking in the streets...
人们走上街头
...offering garlands to the police...
帮警察戴上花环
...and British soldiers.
还有英国军人
Perhaps I have overdone it.
或许我做的太过火了
Good morning, Bapu.
早安，巴布
Don't let him go.
早安，别松手了
If he bumps me, I'm done for.
撞上我，我会倒的
Don't worry, I won't let him go.
放心，我不会松手的
I'm sorry, Mr. Gandhi, sir...
对不起，甘地先生
...but you're under arrest.
我要拘捕你
On what charge?
什么罪名
Sedition.
妨害治安
You can't be serious.
不会是真的吧
This man has just stopped a revolution.
他刚刚阻止了一次革命
That's as may be.
可能吧
I only know what I am charged to perform.
我只知道要奉命行事
I don't believe it!
我不相信
The British can't be that stupid.
就算是英国人 也不可能如此愚蠢
Help me, please.
尼鲁，扶我一下
Mira, you must look after Ba.
米乐曼，要照顾芭
If there is one protest, one riot, a disgrace of any kind...
如果有任何暴动，任何抗议 或者任何羞耻的行为
...I will fast again.
我会再次绝食的
Herman.
赫曼
I have been on many trips.
我旅行过很多次
Monda.
孟戴
This is just another trip.
这只是另一次的旅行罢了
I am at your command.
我敬听吩咐
I know we are not ready for my kind of independence.
我知道印度还没到 我要那种独立的阶段
If I'm sent to jail, perhaps that is the best protest...
如果我被关了，或许正是
...our country can make at this time.
印度最好的一次抗议行动
And, if it helps India, I've never refused His Majesty's hospitality.
我一向不拒绝 英王陛下的招待
Call the prisoner to the bar.
召犯人出庭
"Noncooperation has one aim:
不合作的目的
The overthrow of the government.
就是要推翻政府
Sedition must become our creed.
妨害治安是我们的信条
We must give no quarter...
绝不让步
...nor can we expect any."
否则会无立足之地
- Do you deny writing it? - Not at all.
-你否认是你写的吗 -绝不会否认
And I will save the court's time...
而且我要节省庭上的时间
...my lord, by stating under oath that, to this day...
我发誓到现在
...I believe noncooperation with evil is a duty...
我仍相信 不与罪恶合作是责任
...and that British rule of India is evil.
而英国统治印度是罪恶的
The prosecution rests, my lord.
大人，控方问完了
I presume you are conducting your own defense.
我想你要自己来辩护了
I have no defense, my lord. I am guilty as charged.
我不抗辩，我有罪
And if you truly believe in your system of law...
如果大人真的相信你的法律
...you must inflict on me the severest penalty possible.
那您必须尽量从重量刑
It is impossible for me to ignore that you are in a different category...
我不得不承认 你和我所审判过的人
...from any person I have ever tried...
或者想要审判的
...or am likely to try.
完全不同
Nevertheless, it is my duty to sentence you...
不过职责所在我必须判你
...to six years' imprisonment.
六年徒刑
Lf, however, His Majesty's government should, at some later date...
如果英王的政府 在未来觉得
...see fit to reduce the term...
应该减刑
...no one will be better pleased than I.
那没有人会比我更高兴的
Yes, I'm sure that's exactly what they hoped:
我想他们一定希望能如此
Put him in prison a few years. With luck, he'd be forgotten.
关他几年，运气好的话 人们会忘了他
Maybe they could even subdue him.
甚至能使他屈服
Well, he certainly wasn't forgotten.
不过他可没被遗忘
And as soon as he got out, he was back tramping the countryside...
一出狱就又浪迹各乡村
...preaching nonviolence and demanding a free India.
宣导不要用暴力 要求解放印度
Everyone knows another showdown's coming.
大家都知道 又面临了一个关键时刻
How does an American journalist in Central America...
一个驻中美洲的美国记者
...learn that Gandhi was born in Porbandar anyway?
怎么会知道甘地是波港人
I've been aware of him for a long time.
我留意他很久了
He certainly makes good copy.
他是报导的好材料
The other day, Winston Churchill called him a half-naked Indian fakir.
那天邱吉尔还说他是 半裸的印度苦行僧
I met him once.
我见过他一次
What, you mean Gandhi?
什么，你是指甘地吗
South Africa, a long time ago.
在南非，很久以前了
I wonder if he'll recognize me.
不知道他是否还记得我
What was he like?
当时他是什么样子的
He had a full head of hair then.
那时他有满头的头发
We were a bit like college students, trying to figure everything out.
我们有点像 对什么都想一探究竟的大学生
Well, he must have found some of the answers.
他一定是探出一些究竟了
In every worthy wish of yours, I shall be your helpmate.
我一切都听从你 做你的贤内助…
Helpmate.
贤内助
Take the fourth step, that we may be ever full of joy.
第四步，愿我们永远快乐
I will ever live devoted to you...
我对你终生不渝
...speaking words of love and praying for your happiness.
爱你并祈求你的幸福
Take the fifth step...
第五步
...the walking around a fire...
绕着火走
...that we may serve the people.
我们将服务人群
I will follow close behind you...
我将紧随着你
...and help to serve the people.
帮助你服务人群
Take the sixth step...
第六步
...that we may follow our vows in life.
愿我们终生信守誓言
I will follow you in all our vows and duties.
我会跟随着你 信守所有的誓言与责任
Take the seventh step...
第七步
...that we may ever live as friends.
愿我们终生都是好友
You are my best friend...
你是我的挚友
...my highest guru...
最高的导师
...and my sovereign lord.
和至高无上的主人
And then I put a sweetened wheat cake in her mouth.
然后我放一块甜麦糕 到她的嘴里
And I put a sweetened wheat cake in his mouth.
我放一块甜麦糕 到他的嘴中
And with that, we were pronounced...
然后婚礼完成，我们结为
...man and wife.
夫妻
We were both 13.
那时候我们两个都13岁
It's beautiful.
好美
Even as a boy, I thought so.
我向来也觉得很美
Thank you.
谢谢
Trying to keep up with you is like chasing a jackrabbit.
想跟上你简直像是在追野兔
You've come because you think something is going to happen.
你以为会发生大事 所以大老远赶过来
Is it?
会发生吗
Perhaps.
或许
I've come here to think about it.
我就是来这里考虑这件事的
Do you remember much of South Africa?
你还记得南非的事吗
A great deal.
有，我常想到它
I've traveled so far...
自那我走了很远的路
...and thought so much.
也想了很多
As you can see...
你也看到
...my city is a sea city.
我的家乡靠海
Always full of Hindus...
总是有很多印度教徒
...Muslims...
回教徒
...Sikhs, Jews, Persians.
锡克教徒，犹太教徒，波斯人
My family's sect was the Pranami.
我的家族是婆罗门贵族
Hindu, of course.
自然是信奉印度教了
But in our temple, the priest used to read...
可是在我们的庙里
...from the Muslim Koran...
主持常会读可兰经
...and the Hindu Gita, moving from one to the other...
和印度教经文，轮流念
...as if it mattered not which book was read...
好像什么经文都无所谓似的
...as long as God was worshiped.
只要崇拜神就可以
When I was a boy...
小时候
...I used to sing a song in the temple.
我常在庙里唱一首歌
A true disciple Knows another's woes
真正的信徒会了解
As his own
别人的苦难就如自己的
He bows to all...
尊敬所有的人
...and despises none.
不鄙视任何人
Like all other boys...
我跟其他的小孩一样
...I sang the words...
我唱着歌
...not thinking what they meant...
没思考过歌词的意义
...or how they might influence me.
也没想到 这会对我产生什么影响
I've traveled so far.
我走了那么远
And all I've done is come back...
结果还是回到
...home.
家乡来
Wait a minute.
等一下
You know what you're going to do, don't you?
你知道你要做什么，对不对
It would have been uncivil of me...
要是累你徒劳无返
...to let you make such a long trip for nothing.
我就太失礼了
- Where are you going? - Come.
-你要去哪里 -来吧
- Where are we going? - Back to the ashram.
-我要回阿思朗
Then I'm going to prove to the new Viceroy...
然后我要向新总督证明
...that the King's writ no longer runs in India.
英王对印度不再有统治权了
Salt?
盐
Yes, sir. He's going to march...
是的，他要步行到海边
...to the sea and make salt.
然后开始制盐
There's a royal monopoly...
制造盐
...on the manufacture of salt.
是皇家的专利
It's illegal to make it or sell it...
无政府执照擅自制盐
...without a government license.
或者卖盐都是非法的行为
All right, he's breaking the law.
好吧，他违法了
What will that deprive us of?
我们有什么损失
Two rupees of salt tax?
少点盐税罢了
It's not a serious attack on the revenue.
对政府收入影响很小
Its primary importance is symbolic.
主要是他所象征的意义
Don't patronize me, Charles.
别看扁了我，查尔斯
In this climate, nothing lives without water or salt.
在这种气候下 无水无盐是活不下去的
Our absolute control of it is a control on the pulse...
我们控制盐就是控制了
...of India.
印度的命脉
And that's the basis of this declaration of independence?
这就是“独立宣言”的基本行动吗
The day he sets off...
他开始的那一天
...everyone is supposed to raise the flag of "Free India."
所有的人都要高举新印度国旗
Then he walks 240 miles...
然后他走240里路
...to the sea and makes salt.
到海边开始制盐
I say, ignore it.
我说别理它
Let them raise their damned flags.
让他们举他们天杀的国旗
Let him make his salt.
让他去制盐
It's only symbolic...
要我们把它当为象征
...if we choose to make it so.
它才是如此
He'll arrive...
他将在
...at the sea on the anniversary of the Massacre of Amritsar.
安里沙大屠杀周年 那天到达海边
General Edgar is right.
艾加将军说的对
Ignore it.
别理它
Mr. Gandhi will find...
甘地先生会发现
...it takes a great deal more than...
一把盐
...a pinch of salt to bring down the British Empire.
是不可能打垮大英帝国的
You've done me a great service.
你帮了我很大的忙
Not at all, sir.
不客气
It would be uncivil for us...
如果让你走那么远
...to let you make such a long trip for nothing.
还徒劳无返就太失礼了
We'll go.
我们走
Long live Gandhiji!
甘地万岁…
Is it over if they arrest you now?
如果他们现在逮捕你 一切就结束了吗
Not if they arrest me...
即使逮捕我
...or 1,000 or 10,000.
或逮捕一千 一万个人也不会结束
It's not only generals who know how to plan campaigns.
不是只有将军才懂谋定而后动
What if they don't arrest you? What if they don't react at all?
如果他们不逮捕你呢 如果他们毫无反应呢
Something for your notebook:
你记下来：
The function of a civil resister is to provoke response.
民族运动要激起反应才有作用
And we will continue to provoke...
我们一定会一直努力下去
...until they respond or they change the law.
直到他们有所反应或改变法律
They are not in control. We are.
控制权不在他们手中 而是在我们手中
That is the strength of civil resistance.
这就是民族运动的力量
Vince!
文思
- What did he say? - He said he's in control.
-他说什么 -他说一切在他的控制之中
Do you intend to walk all the way?
你打算一直走下去吗
It's the only way I can get the story.
这样才能报导这件事
Besides, my name is Walker.
而且我姓的意思是“走路”
"My name is Walker."
你姓“走路”
My dear Mrs. Naidu!
亲爱的纳杜夫人
Man needs salt...
人类需要盐
...as he needs air and water.
就如同需要空气和水一样
This salt comes from the Indian Ocean.
这盐来自印度洋
Let every Indian claim it as his right.
所有的印度人都有权享用
And so once more, the man of nonviolence...
再一次的，这个非暴力人士
...has challenged the might of the British Empire.
又向大英帝国强权挑战
They're making it everywhere, sir.
到处都在制盐
Mobs of them...
成群结队
...publicly.
而且是公开的
The congress leaders are selling it on the streets of Delhi.
国会领袖在新德里的街头卖盐
We're being made fools of, sir...
大家都在看我们的笑话
...around the world.
是全世界
Isn't there any instruction from London?
伦敦没有指示吗
We're required to stop it.
他们要求我们阻止这件事
And stop it we will!
我们一定要阻止
I don't care if we fill the jails. Stop it!
就算监狱爆满也在所不惜
Arrest anyone, any rank...
逮捕所有的人，不论任何阶级
...except Gandhi.
除了甘地
We'll cut the strength from under him.
我们要切断他的力量
And then we'll deal with the Mahatma.
然后再来对付这位圣雄
Jump to it!
快走！
Clear this beach!
清除海滩
Don't hit back!
西亚，别还手
No violence!
别使用暴力
There must be 100,000 under arrest.
逮捕了十万人
- And it still goes on. - Who's leading them?
-还在持续中 -谁在领导他们
I don't know. Nehru, Patel...
我不知道，尼鲁，彼帖
...almost every congress official is in jail...
所有的国会官员都被逮捕了
...and their wives and their children.
还有他们的妻儿
We've even arrested Nehru's mother.
我们甚至逮捕了尼鲁的母亲
Has there been any violence?
有任何的暴力行为吗
In Peshawar, the deputy police commissioner...
白夏瓦的副警察局长
...lost his head and opened fire with a machine gun.
昏了头用机关枪扫射民众
But he's facing a disciplinary court.
不过他已经被送交军事法庭了
You can't expect things like that not to happen.
这种事是意料之中的
The question was intended...
我想他是问
...to discover whether there was any violence on their side.
对方有没有任何暴力行为
No, sir.
没有…
I'm afraid not.
恐怕是没有
Perhaps if we arrested Gandhi, it might...
或许逮捕了甘地就可以…
He's addressed this letter directly to you, has he?
这封信是他本人写给你的
Yes, sir, he has.
是的
The usual thing:
相同的事
"India's salt belongs to India."
印度的盐属于印度所有
Then he says flatly...
他还明白表示明天
...that he will lead a raid tomorrow on the Dharasana salt works.
他要亲自领队到达兰沙纳制盐
Thank him for his letter...
多谢他的来信
...and put him in jail.
把他关起来
Yes, sir.
是
It'll be my pleasure.
我乐意之至
And Fields?
菲尔斯
Keep that salt works open.
让他们继续制盐
Yes, sir.
是的，长官
I'm sorry, sir.
对不起
My orders are to allow regular staff only through these gates.
不过我奉令 只准一般员工进入
Very well.
很好
We will receive them in his name.
我们要代他承受 也为他承受苦难
And for his sake, we will not raise a hand.
我们绝不还手
Long live Mahatma Gandhi!
圣雄甘地万岁
Long live Gandhiji!
甘地万岁…
We are ready!
我们准备好了
I want firmness and discipline.
你们要坚定，而且严守纪律
Take your positions.
好，各就各位
To your mark.
准备好
Forward!
部队前进
Last night at midnight...
昨天午夜
...they took Gandhiji from us.
他们带走甘地先生
They expect us to lose heart...
想让我们惊慌
...or to fight back.
出手还击
We will do neither!
我们绝不会如此
On your guard!
戒备
No, sir. The gate is closed!
不行，大门关闭
"They walked...
他们走上前
...both Hindu and Muslim alike...
印度教徒和回教徒并肩而走
...with heads held high...
抬头挺胸
...without any hope of escape...
面对无可逃遁的
...from injury or death.
受伤或死亡
It went on and on into the night."
一直持续到夜晚
Stop.
句点
"Women carried the wounded and broken bodies from the road...
女人抬走死伤者
...until they dropped from exhaustion."
直到累的筋疲力竭
Stop.
句点
"But still, it went on and on.
可是一切仍持续下去
Whatever moral ascendancy the West held...
不论西方原有所谓的道德优势
...was lost here today.
今天已经一切丧失了
India is free...
印度自由了
...for she has taken all that steel and cruelty can give...
因为它承受了一切苦难与折磨
...and she has neither cringed nor retreated."
既不屈服，也不退缩
I am aware...
我知道
...that I must have given you much cause for irritation...
我一定让你苦恼不安
...Your Excellency.
大人
I hope it will not stand between us as men.
希望你不会心存介蒂
I am instructed to request your attendance...
甘地先生，我奉令请你参加
...at an all-government conference in London...
伦敦召开的国协大会
...to discuss...
以讨论
...the possible independence...
印度独立的
...of India.
可能性
Only recently released from prison...
最近才被释放的
...Mahatma Gandhi leaves Bombay...
圣雄甘地自孟买起程
...on the S.S. Rajputana to attend...
搭雷普塔纳号 参加
...the conference on Indian independence...
有关印度独立的圆桌会议
...called by Prime Minister Ramsay MacDonald.
这个会议是由麦当诺首相召开
Mr. Gandhi, the sole Indian Congress Party delegate...
印度国会唯一的代表甘地先生
...is staying at Kingsley Hall in the East End of London...
在此会谈期间
...for the duration of the talks.
住宿伦敦东区的金士利大厦
And he's seen here amongst local cockneys...
你们能在伦敦的人群中看到他
...who have taken him to their hearts.
伦敦人衷心的喜欢他
Besides attending the conference...
除了开会，剩余时间
...he has found time to meet political and religious leaders...
他还与政教界的领袖会谈
...like Mr. Lloyd George...
例如洛德乔治
...and the Archbishop of Canterbury, Mr. George Bernard Shaw...
天主教总教主，萧伯纳
...and Mr. Charlie Chaplin.
张伯伦
He journeyed last week from Kingsley Hall...
上星期
...to accept an invitation to tea from King George and Queen Mary...
他接受英王皇后陛下的邀请
...at Buckingham Palace before attending the conference.
由金士利往白金汉宫 接受午茶的款待
And I would emphasize that I think our first duty...
我要强调我们首要职责
...is to recognize that there is not one India...
是在认清印度不只是一个
...but several.
而是好几个
A Hindu India...
有印度教的印度
...a Muslim India...
回教徒的印度
...and an India of princely states.
有王公贵族所属的印度
And all these must be respected...
全都必须顾虑到
...and cared for.
照顾到
Not just one.
而不只顾虑其中一个
Mr. Gandhi, who has been attending...
前来伦敦参加印度独立
...the London Round Table Conference on Indian Independence...
圆桌会议的甘地先生
...journeyed north to visit a cotton mill.
今天前往北部 参观一间棉布纺织厂
Although not dressed for the Lancashire climate...
虽然穿着不适合兰开夏的气候
...Mr. Gandhi received a warm welcome from mill workers...
但是甘地先生仍受到工人 热烈诚挚的欢迎
...before heading back south...
之后在南下
...for a final meeting with Mr. MacDonald.
与麦当诺先生做最后的会谈
The prime minister said the talks were both constructive and frank.
会后，首相说这件会议 具建设性且开诚布公
So farewell, Mr. Gandhi.
再见了，甘地先生
And bon voyage!
一路顺风
So the truth is, after all your travels...
事实上你是徒劳无返
...after all your efforts...
白费心力
...they've stopped the campaign and sent you back empty-handed.
他们停止我们的运动 让你空手而回
They're only clinging to old dreams...
他们只是难舍旧梦
...and trying to split us in the old way.
想用老套来分化我们
But the will has gone.
可是坚定的意志不再
Independence will fall like a ripe apple.
独立宛如熟透的苹果 快要掉下来
The only question is when and how.
只是时间的早晚 还有用什么策略
Well, I say, when is now!
我说就是现在
And we will determine how.
我们将决定策略
Precisely.
没错
Bapu, she is limping again.
巴布，它又跛了
It's only a sprain.
只是扭到了
Take her to the river. We'll make a mud pack for her.
带它去河边 我来用泥巴帮它敷一下
Go. I won't be a moment.
去吧，我等会儿会过去
They are preparing for war.
他们在战备状态
I will not support it.
我不会支持他们
But I do not intend to take advantage of their danger.
不过也不想趁人之危
That's when you take advantage.
应该要把握时机
That is just another way of hitting back.
那样也算是一种还击
We've come a long way together with the British.
我们和英国同舟共济很久了
When they leave, we want to see them off as friends.
希望能送别友人般的 与他们挥别
Now, if you'll excuse me, there is something I must attend to.
失陪了，我还有别的事要做
Mud packs.
敷泥巴
I have been instructed to inquire...
甘地先生，我奉令来这里
...as to the subject of your speech tonight.
询问你今晚演讲的主题
The value of goat's milk in daily diet.
羊奶对日常饮食的重要性
But you can be sure that I will also speak against war.
不过可以确定我会谈到反战
Sorry, that can't be permitted.
对不起，不准提到这个
Corporal!
下士
It's all right, Mrs. Gandhi.
没关系，甘地夫人
I have orders to return with you and your companion to the ashram.
我奉令护送你们回去阿思朗
If you take my husband, I intend to speak in his place.
如果你带走我的先生 我将代他上台演讲
Hold it a second, will you?
停一下，好吗
It was the Aga Khan's palace before they turned it into a prison.
这里原本是阿卡汉宫 现在被他们改为监狱
They're holding Gandhi and a number of the congress politicians there.
这里关着甘地和几位国会领袖
Pandit Nehru and the others are up at Ahmednagar Fort.
尼鲁跟其他人 被关在阿哈纳卡堡
Not bad for a prison, eh?
这种监狱不错吧
I guess no place is good if you're locked in.
不过我想 被关在那里都不是件好事
Your timing's pretty lucky.
你来的正是时候
They had him cut off from the press.
他们原本不准他和新闻界会面
But his personal secretary died, so they let up on restrictions.
可是上个月他的私人秘书死了 所以才放宽限制
Yes, I have heard of Life magazine.
我听说过“生活杂志”
I've even heard of Margaret Bourke-White.
甚至也听过您的大名 玛格丽特布鲁克怀特
But I don't know why either should be interested in an old man...
可是我不明白 你跟你的杂志为什么会
...sitting alone in prison...
当外面的世界正打的天翻地覆时
...while the rest of the world is blowing itself to pieces.
对一个坐牢的孤单老头有兴趣
You're the only man I know who makes his own clothes.
你是我知道 唯一自己织布缝衣的男人
But for me, that's not much of an accomplishment.
不过这实在算不上什么成就
Prison is rather agreeable to me.
坐牢我已经习惯了
And there is no doubt that after the war...
无疑的，战后
...independence will come.
一定可以独立
My only worry...
我担心的是
...is what shape it will take.
会是什么状况
- Jinnah has... - Stop!
-吉纳已经… -停一下
I'm sorry, but... Could you come forward, please?
对不起，能不能请往前一点
- Come, come. - Just up to the railing.
-来吧 -靠着扶手
Thank you very much.
谢谢
Now, sorry.
对不起
Go on, just as you were. "What shape it will take..."
请继续说下去，什么状况
Jinnah has what?
吉纳怎么样
Jinnah has cooperated with the British.
吉纳已经跟英国人合作
It has given him power and the freedom to speak.
得到权力，也有说话自由
And he's filled the Muslims with fears...
这使得回教徒人心惶惶
...of what will happen to them...
担心在印度教统治下
...in a country that is predominantly Hindu.
他们会有什么下场
And that I find hard to bear...
这件事让我难以忍受
...even in prison.
即使在牢里也如此
It's very hard for me to see this...
我很难了解
...as a solution to the 20th century's problems.
这就是20世纪 解决问题的方法
I have friends who keep telling me...
有些朋友一直告诉我
...how much it costs them to keep me in poverty.
他们以多大的代价 才换来我的贫困
But I know happiness does not come with things...
可是我知道 物质享受不能带来幸福
...even 20th century things.
即使是20世纪的物质享受
It can come from work and pride in what you do.
而是来自工作和你的所作所为
India lives in her villages...
印度人住在村落中
...and the terrible poverty there can only be removed...
只有再恢复他们的原有技术
...if their local skills can be revived.
才能改善那种贫困
Poverty is the worst form of violence.
贫穷才是最糟糕的暴力
And a constructive program is the only...
只有建设计划才能
...nonviolent solution to India's agony.
不用暴力地解决印度的痛苦
It will not necessarily be progress for India...
如果只是由西方
...if she simply...
进口一些不幸
...imports the unhappiness of the West.
对其并非进步
But do you really believe you could use nonviolence...
你真的相信可以用非暴力方法
...against someone like Hitler?
对付希特勒这种人吗
Not without defeats and great pain.
会有挫折也会有极大的痛苦
But are there no defeats in this war?
但是在这场战争中 就没有挫折
No pain?
没有痛苦了吗
What you cannot do...
人们不能接受不公平的事
...is accept injustice from Hitler or anyone.
不论对方是希特勒或是任何人
You must make the injustice visible.
一定要努力让人看到 这个不公平的事情
Be prepared to die like a soldier to do so.
并且愿意以身殉之
Is this what I'm meant to end up with here?
这个弄出来应该是这样的吗
No, that's what you get for distracting me.
不，你令我分心的结果就是这样
What do you expect when you talk like that?
你说那些话 还能期望我弄出什么结果
I expect you to show as much patience as I am now.
我期望你能和我一样有耐心
Turn slowly and pull it gently.
慢慢的转，轻轻的拉
And that includes the life of women.
也包括了女人的生活
Bapu has always said...
巴布常说
...there were two kinds of slavery in India:
印度有两种奴隶制度
One for women, one for the untouchables.
一种是女人的 一种是低等贱民的
And he has always fought against both.
他一向反对这两个制度
Does it rankle, being separated in this way?
这样分开会不会难过
In Hindu philosophy...
印度哲学里中
...the way to God...
要接近神
...is to free yourself of possessions...
必须放弃财产
...and the passions.
与情欲
Bapu has always struggled to find the way to God.
巴布一直努力想接近神
Do you mean that he gave up married life?
你是说他放弃了婚姻生活
Four times he tried...
他试过四次
...and failed.
都失败了
But then he took a solemn vow.
不过他发过重誓…
And he's never broken it?
他从未违背过吗
Not yet.
还没有
I've got permission to move her.
我得到准许可以带走她 他也可以走了
I'm very sorry, sir.
抱歉
She's had a massive thrombosis. It's a serious heart attack.
她心肌梗塞 很严重的心脏病
She'll never survive the trip.
移动她，她就绝对活不了
I think it's better if we just keep her here and hope.
我想最好别动她 祈祷希望有转机
It's time for my walk.
我该去散步了
I won't be long.
我马上会回来
Guard...
仪队
...present arm!
举枪
We have come to crown victory with friendship...
我们来此友善的为总督加冕
...to assist at the birth of an independent India...
在印度独立日予以协助
...and to welcome her as an equal member...
并且欢迎成为
...in the British Commonwealth of Nations.
大英国协中地位平等的一份子
I am here to see that I am the last British Viceroy...
我将是最后一任英国总督
...ever to have the honor of such a reception.
很高兴有如此的欢迎仪式
I am not concerned about the independence of India.
甘地，我不管印度独立与否
I'm concerned about the slavery of the Muslims.
我关心的是回教徒被奴役 我不会袖手旁观
Please, Mr. Jinnah.
拜托，吉纳先生
I won't stand by to see the mastery of the British...
眼见印度教
...replaced by the mastery of the Hindus.
取英国而代之来统治印度
Muslim and Hindu are the right and left eye of India.
回教徒，印度教正如印度的 左右眼
No one will be master, no one slave.
不会有主奴之分
The world is not made of Mahatma Ghandis.
这个世界不是人人都像你
I'm talking about the real world.
我在说真实的世界
- How the... - The real India has...
-如何… -真正的印度
...Muslims and Hindus in every village and every city.
在每个村庄城市 都有回教徒和印度教徒
How do you propose to separate them?
你打算如何把他们分开
Where there is a Muslim majority...
回教徒占多数的地方
...that will be Pakistan.
独立为巴基斯坦
The rest is your India.
其他的就是你们的印度
My dear Jinnah...
亲爱的吉纳
...the Muslims are in a majority on two different sides of the country.
回教徒占多数的地方 分隔在印度的两方
Let us worry about Pakistan. You worry about India.
让我们担心巴基斯坦 你们去担心印度吧
Gentlemen...
各位
...I think perhaps we should recommence.
我想或许该继续
Death to Jinnah!
吉纳去死…
Thank God, they've stopped.
感谢神，终于停了
Manu, Aba.
玛妞，阿芭
I'm your granduncle...
我虽然是你们的叔公
...but I can still walk either of you into the ground.
我能比你们走得远
And I don't need to be pampered in this way.
我不要人家这样照顾我
Finish your quota of spinning.
去纺完你们的纱
Bapu, please don't do it.
巴布，请别这么做
What do you want me not to do?
你叫我别做什么
Not to meet with Mr. Jinnah?
不去和吉纳会谈吗
I am a Muslim...
我是回教徒
...and a Hindu...
也是印度教徒
...and a Christian and a Jew.
是基督教徒，也是犹太教徒
And so are all of you.
你们大家都一样
When you wave those flags and shout...
你们挥舞旗子大喊大叫
...you send fear into the hearts of your brothers.
使你的同胞丧胆
That is not the India I want.
我不要印度这样
Stop it!
停止吧
For God's sake, stop it.
看在老天的份上停止吧
If you've finished your prayers...
如果你们祷告完了
...perhaps we could begin our business.
或许可以开始谈正事了
My dear Jinnah...
亲爱的吉纳先生
...you and I are brothers...
你我如手足
...born of the same mother India.
都是同一个母亲，印度所生的
If you have fears...
如果你有所畏惧
...I want to put them at rest.
我将使你不再畏惧
Begging the understanding of my friends...
恳求我的朋友体谅我
...I am asking Panditji to stand down.
我要求潘迪尼鲁下台
I want you to be the first prime minister of India...
由你担任印度第一总理
...to name your entire cabinet...
你可以指定所有内阁人选
...to make the head of every government department a Muslim.
可以任命回教徒 担任各政府部门的首长
For me and the rest...
我和其他人…
...if that is what you want...
如果这是你所愿的
...we will accept it.
我和其他人都愿意遵从
But out there...
可是外面
...already there is rioting...
已经开始发生暴动
...because Hindus fear you are going to give too much away.
因为印度教徒担心 你会太过让步
If you did this...
你这么做
...no one would control it.
没人能控制得了
No one.
没有人
It is your choice.
由你决定
Do you want an independent India and an independent Pakistan...
你要独立的印度 和独立的巴基斯坦
...or do you want civil war?
还是要内战
Jinnah! Jinnah!
吉纳…
What you did in Noakhali, Bapu, was a miracle.
你在诺亚克哈里的成功 是个奇迹
But millions are on the move...
可是上百万人都加入内战
...and no one can count the dead.
死伤不计其数
In Calcutta, it's like civil war.
加尔各答有如内战
The Muslims rose and there was a bloodbath.
回教徒起而暴动 血洗印度教徒
Now the Hindus are taking revenge.
现在印度教徒起而复仇
If we can't stop it...
如果不阻止
...there'll be no hope for the Hindus left in Pakistan.
巴基斯坦的 印度教徒会全被杀光的
An eye for an eye, making the whole world blind.
以眼还眼 使整个世界都盲目了
Aren't there any troops to spare?
没有军队可以派了吗
Nothing.
没有了
The divisions in Bombay and Delhi can hardly keep the peace now.
孟买和新德里 连当地的和平都维持不了
And each fresh bit of news creates another wave of madness.
而且一有新消息 双方就又疯狂的彼此攻打起来
We could cut all news off.
可以封锁所有的新闻
Bapu, please, where are you going?
巴布，请你…你要去哪里
I don't want to hear more.
我不要听了
We need your help.
我们需要你的帮助
There is nothing I can give.
我什么也帮不上
Where are you going?
你要去哪里
Calcutta.
加尔各答
If I had shunned death or feared it, I would not be here now...
如果我避免死亡或者怕死的话 也就不会来这里了
...nor would you be concerned for me.
你不必为我担心
But, sir, please.
但是先生
I don't have the men to protect you...
我无法派人保护你
...not in a Muslim house, not this quarter.
你住回教徒家，在这区不行
I'm staying with the friend of a friend and...
我住在一个朋友的朋友家里
Death to Muslims!
杀死回教徒…
Why are you staying at the home of a Muslim?
你为什么住在回教徒家里
They are murderers!
他们是凶手
They killed my family!
他们杀了我的家人
Get out of Calcutta, Gandhi!
滚出加尔各答，甘地
Death to Muslims!
杀死回教徒…
Prime Minister.
总理
Why must I read news like this in the paper?
为什么我要看报纸 才能知道这件事
Inform Sardar Patel. Arrange a plane.
通知彼帖安排飞机
We will go Friday.
我们星期五去
Four days, sir?
四天后，长官
Sardar, you have gained weight.
彼帖，你胖了
You must join me in the fast.
和我一起绝食
If I fast, I die.
如果我绝食就会死
If you fast, people go to all sorts of trouble...
你绝食人们会费尽一切力量
...to keep you alive.
让你不死
Bapu, forgive me, I've cheated.
巴布，原谅我，我欺骗了你
I could have come earlier...
我原本可以早点来的
...but your fast has helped.
可是你绝食有所帮助
These last days, people's minds have begun to turn to this bed...
这几天人们转而关心你
...and away from the atrocities.
而不再互相攻击了
But now...
可是现在
...it is enough.
够了
All that has happened is that I've grown a little thinner.
唯一发生的就是我瘦了一点
Tomorrow, 5,000 Muslim students...
明天五千个回教徒学生
...of all ages...
是各年龄层
...are marching here, in Calcutta, for peace.
将在加尔各答为和平游行
And 5,000 Hindu students are marching with them.
有五千个印度教徒学生 也会和他们一起游行
I'm glad.
我很高兴
But it will not be enough.
可是还是不够
You are not so young anymore.
你不再年轻了
Don't worry for me.
别担心我
I cannot watch the destruction of all that I've lived for.
我不能眼睁睁的看 我一生的奋斗付诸流水
Death to Gandhi!
杀死甘地！
Who dares say such things?
谁敢说这种话？
Who?
是谁？
You kill me first!
你得先杀了我
Come!
来呀！
Where are you?
你在哪里
Kill me first!
先把我杀了
His pulse is very irregular. The kidneys aren't functioning.
他的脉搏很不规则 肾脏已经失去功能了
I have brought Mr. Suhrawardy.
我带舒拉瓦地先生来
It was he who called on the Muslims to rise.
是他号召回教徒起而暴动
He is now telling them...
现在他叫他们
...to go back to their homes...
放下武器
...to lay down their arms.
回家去
Think what you can do by living...
想想你活着能做些什么
...that you cannot do by dying.
如果死了就什么也不能做
What do you want?
你还要什么？
That the fighting will stop.
战斗停止
That you make me believe...
让我相信
...that it will never start again.
再也不会发生这种事
Sometimes...
有时
...it is when you are quite without hope...
在绝望中
...and in utter darkness...
完全不知所从
...that God comes to the rescue.
神会来拯救你们
Gandhiji...
甘地
...is dying...
因为我们的疯狂
...because of our madness.
要死了
Put away your revenge.
别再报复了
What good will come of more killing?
再多的杀戮有什么用
Have the courage to do...
提起勇气
...what you know is right.
做你知道是正确的事
For God's sake...
看在老天的份上
...let us embrace...
让我们拥抱吧
...like brothers.
像兄弟般似的
It's our promise.
我们保证
We stop.
我们不打了
Hindu swords.
印度剑
It's a promise.
这就是保证
Go.
走吧
God be with you.
神保佑你
Here, eat!
吃吧
I'm going to hell...
我快下地狱了
...but not with your death on my soul.
可是不想担负杀你的罪名
Only God decides who goes to hell.
只有神能决定谁该下地狱
I killed a child.
我杀了一个小孩
I smashed his head against a wall.
我抓住他的头往墙上撞碎了
Why?
为什么
They killed my son.
他们杀了我的儿子
My boy.
我的孩子
The Muslims killed my son!
回教徒杀了我的儿子
I know a way out of hell.
我知道不入地狱的方法
Find a child.
找一个孩子
A child whose mother and father have been killed.
一个父母都被杀死的孩子
A little boy about this high...
一个小男孩，大概这么高
...and raise him as your own.
把他当成你的儿子抚养
Only be sure that he is a Muslim...
只是一定要确定他是个回教徒
...and that you raise him as one.
而且要把他教养成回教徒
Go.
走吧…
God bless you.
上帝保佑你
Bapu?
巴布…
There's been no fighting...
各地都没战斗了
...anywhere.
每个地方
It's stopped.
都停止了
The madness has stopped.
疯狂杀戮停止了
It's foolish...
如果是为了救我这个老人家
...if it's just to save the life of an old man.
这样就太傻了
In every temple and mosque...
人们都去各个印度庙宇 和清真寺立誓
...they have pledged to die...
他们宁死
...before they lift a hand against each other.
也不会攻击对方了
It is true, Bapu.
是真的，巴布
Everywhere.
到处都是这样
Maulana, my friend...
莫拉纳，我的朋友
...could I have some orange juice?
能不能给我一点橘子汁
Then you and I...
然后我们两个
...will take a piece of bread together.
一起吃片面包
He will be saying prayers in the garden.
他会在花园祈祷
That is how you eat muli.
应该这样吃的
I'm not sure that I want to be remembered that way.
我想人们不会要记得 我这个样子吧
Don't worry. With luck, you may not be.
放心，运气好就不会
No, he will be remembered for tempting fate.
不会的，世人会记得的 他曾与命运赌博
Mickey Mouse!
米老鼠
So you really are going to Pakistan then?
那你真的要去巴基斯坦了
You are a stubborn man.
你真顽固
I'm simply going to prove...
我只是要证明给
...to Hindus here and Muslims there...
这边的印度教徒 和那边的回教徒看
...that the only devils in the world are those...
天下本无事
...running around in our own hearts.
全都是心理作祟
And that is where all our battles ought to be fought.
我们大家都应该努力 驱除这种心理障碍
So what kind of warrior...
在这场战争中
...have you been in that warfare?
你是哪种战士呢
Not a very good one.
不太好的那种
That's why I have so much tolerance...
所以我才能容忍
...for the other scoundrels of the world.
世上其他的恶棍
Sardar?
彼帖
Ask Panditji to consider what we've discussed.
请尼鲁考虑我们讨论过的事
- Enough! - One more.
-够了 -再一张
You're a temptress.
你是诱惑者
Just an admirer.
只是个仰慕者
Nothing's more dangerous...
那就危险了
...especially for an old man.
尤其是对一个老头子
There's a sadness about him.
他很忧愁
He thinks he's failed.
他自己觉得失败了
Why?
为什么
If anything's proven him right, it's these last months.
上个月发生的 一切都证明他是对的
I may be blinded by my love for him...
我可能因为太爱他而盲目
...but I believe...
可是我相信
...when we most needed it...
在我们最需要的时候
...he offered the world a way out of madness.
他带领我们远离疯狂
But he doesn't see it.
可是他自己不知道
Neither does the world.
世人也不知道
Brother, Bapu is already late for prayers.
兄弟，巴布祷告已经迟了
Oh, God!
上帝
When I despair...
当我绝望时
...I remember...
我会想起
...that all through history...
在历史上
...the way of truth and love has always won.
只有真理和爱能得胜
There have been tyrants and murderers...
历史上有很多暴君和凶手
...and for a time, they can seem invincible...
在短期内或许是所向无敌的
...but in the end, they always fall.
但是终就总是会失败
Think of it.
好好想一想
Always.
永远都是这样